[{"ID": "0331fc28","Question": "The human brain is primed to recognize faces—so much so that, due to a perceptual tendency called pareidolia, ______ will even ﬁnd faces in clouds, wooden doors, pieces of fruit, and other faceless inanimate objects. Researcher Susan Magsamen has focused her work on better understanding this everyday phenomenon. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "she","B": "they","C": "it","D": "those","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. 'It' is a singular pronoun used to stand in for objects. Since the antecedent in this case is the singular noun phrase 'the human brain,' 'it' is a perfect pronoun to use here. Choice A is incorrect. Although 'she' is a singular pronoun, it is reserved for people and animals, not objects like 'the human brain.' Choice B is incorrect. 'They' is a plural pronoun, but we need a singular pronoun to represent the antecedent 'the human brain.' Choice D is incorrect. 'Those' is a plural pronoun, but we need a singular pronoun to represent the antecedent 'the human brain.'","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "03bf5d57","Question": "Gathering accurate data on water ﬂow in the United States is challenging because of the country’s millions of miles of ______ the volume and speed of water at any given location can vary drastically over time. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "waterways and the fact that,","B": "waterways, and the fact that,","C": "waterways, and, the fact that","D": "waterways and the fact that","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation within two coordinated noun phrases. When, as in this case, a noun phrase (“the country’s millions of miles of waterways”) is coordinated with another noun phrase (“the fact”) followed by an integrated relative clause (“that the volume...time”), no punctuation is needed. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed. Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "058915b4","Question": "Known for her massive photorealistic paintings of African American ﬁgures ﬂoating or swimming in pools, Calida Garcia ______ was the logical choice to design the book cover for Ta-Nehisi Coates’s The Water Dancer, a novel about an African American man who can travel great distances through water. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Rawles—","B": "Rawles:","C": "Rawles,","D": "Rawles","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a subject and a verb. When, as in this case, a subject (“Calida Garcia Rawles”) is immediately followed by a verb (“was”), no punctuation is needed. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "088f0914","Question": "If you try on one of artist Nick Cave’s signature Soundsuits, you can expect to swish, rustle, or clang every time you move. Cave makes his suits out of found objects, everything from ceramic birds to broken record players. He carefully considers the sound an object makes before using ______ in a suit. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "this","B": "that","C": "these","D": "it","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested here is pronoun-antecedent agreement. The singular pronoun 'it' agrees in number with the singular antecedent 'object.' Choice A is incorrect. The singular pronoun 'this' is used to refer to a speciﬁc thing, but here there is no speciﬁc object being referred to. Instead, the sentence is referring back to a hypothetical object that Cave might use in a Soundsuit. Choice B is incorrect. The singular pronoun 'that' is used to refer to a speciﬁc thing, but here there is no speciﬁc object being referred to. Instead, the sentence is referring back to a hypothetical object that Cave might use in a Soundsuit. Choice C is incorrect because the plural pronoun 'these' doesn’t agree in number with the singular antecedent 'object.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "0979f82f","Question": "Despite being cheap, versatile, and easy to produce, ______ they are made from nonrenewable petroleum, and most do not biodegrade in landﬁlls. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "there are two problems associated with commercial plastics:","B": "two problems are associated with commercial plastics:","C": "commercial plastics’ two associated problems are that","D": "commercial plastics have two associated problems:","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice ensures that the modifying phrase “despite being cheap, versatile, and easy to produce” appears immediately before the noun it modiﬁes, “commercial plastics,” clearly establishing that the commercial plastics—and not another noun in the sentence—are being described as cheap, versatile, and easy to produce. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the function word “there” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically and confusingly suggests that “there” is cheap, versatile, and easy to produce. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun “two problems” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the “problems” are cheap, versatile, and easy to produce. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “commercial plastics’ two associated problems” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the “problems” are cheap, versatile, and easy to produce.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "0afd235c","Question": "Bonnie Buratti of NASA’s Jet Propulsion Laboratory ______ data about Saturn’s rings collected by the Cassini spacecraft when she made an interesting discovery: the tiny moons embedded between and within Saturn’s rings are shaped by the buildup of ring material on the moons’ surfaces. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "studies","B": "has been studying","C": "will study","D": "was studying","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense in a sentence. In this choice, the past progressive tense verb “was studying” is consistent with the other past tense verbs (e.g., “made” and “collected”) used to describe Buratti’s discovery. Further, the past progressive tense correctly indicates that an ongoing action in the past was occurring (she was studying) at the same time that another event occurred in the past (she made an interesting discovery). Choice A is incorrect because the present tense verb “studies” isn’t consistent with the past tense verbs used to describe Buratti’s discovery. Choice B is incorrect because the present perfect progressive tense verb “has been studying” isn’t consistent with the past tense verbs used to describe Buratti’s discovery. Choice C is incorrect because the future tense verb “will study” isn’t consistent with the past tense verbs used to describe Buratti’s discovery.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "0ba6d65d","Question": "Fans of science ﬁction will ______ multiple references to classic sci-ﬁ stories in Janelle Monáe’s song lyrics, including her recurring nods to the plot of the 1927 sci-ﬁ ﬁlm Metropolis. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "appreciate the","B": "appreciate. The","C": "appreciate, the","D": "appreciate: the","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested here is punctuation between a verb and object. No punctuation is needed between the verb ('appreciate') and its object ('the multiple references...'). The object helps complete the idea of the verb—in this case, it explains what fans of science ﬁction will appreciate—and any punctuation between the two results in an ungrammatical sentence. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and its object. Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and its object. Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and its object.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "0c6083cb","Question": "Luci Tapahonso is the inaugural poet laureate of the Navajo Nation. Her book Sáanii Dahataal/The Women Are Singing—a combination of ﬁction and memoir, poetry and ______ serves as a testament to her versatility as a writer. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "prose;","B": "prose","C": "prose,","D": "prose—","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. “A combination of ﬁction and memoir, poetry and prose” is a nonessential supplement, so it needs to be set off from the rest of the sentence with a pair of matching punctuation marks. We already have a dash at the beginning of the supplement, so we need to add a dash at the end of the supplement to match. Choice A is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. “A combination of ﬁction and memoir, poetry and prose” is a nonessential supplement, so it needs to be set off from the rest of the sentence with a pair of matching punctuation marks. We already have a dash at the beginning of the supplement, so we need to add a dash at the end of the supplement to match. Choice B is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. “A combination of ﬁction and memoir, poetry and prose” is a nonessential supplement, so it needs to be set off from the rest of the sentence with a pair of matching punctuation marks. We already have a dash at the beginning of the supplement, so we need to add a dash at the end of the supplement to match. Choice C is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. “A combination of ﬁction and memoir, poetry and prose” is a nonessential supplement, so it needs to be set off from the rest of the sentence with a pair of matching punctuation marks. We already have a dash at the beginning of the supplement, so we need to add a dash at the end of the supplement to match.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "0d397df2","Question": "A group of ecologists led by Axel Mithöfer at the Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology in Germany examined the defensive responses of two varieties of the sweet potato ______ TN57, which is known for its insect resistance, and TN66, which is much more susceptible to pests. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "plant.","B": "plant;","C": "plant","D": "plant:","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between a main clause and a supplementary phrase. In this choice, a colon is correctly used to mark the boundary between the main clause (“A group…plant”) and the supplementary element (“TN57…pests”) and to introduce the following elaboration on the speciﬁc varieties of sweet potato plants that were examined. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with “TN57.” Choice B is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join the main clause (“A group…plant”) and the supplementary element (“TN57…pests”). A semicolon is conventionally used to join two main clauses, whereas a colon is conventionally used to introduce an element that explains or ampliﬁes the information in the preceding clause. Choice C is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the main clause (“A group...plant”) and the supplementary element (“TN57...pests”) with appropriate punctuation.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "0d590843","Question": "Detroit natives Timothy Paule and Nicole Lindsey have combined their two passions, Detroit and beekeeping, to improve the health of their city’s ﬂowers and other vegetation. In 2017, the couple converted a vacant lot in the city into an ______ in the years that followed they acquired nine additional lots and established more than 35 hives. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "apiary,","B": "apiary, and","C": "apiary and","D": "apiary","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. Both clauses in this sentence could stand alone as complete sentences, which means they are both independent clauses. This choice uses a comma plus a coordinating conjunction to link them together, which is one of the correct ways to link two independent clauses. Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence error. Both clauses in this sentence could stand alone as complete sentences, which means they are both independent clauses. A comma by itself is not enough punctuation to link two independent clauses. Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence error. Both clauses in this sentence could stand alone as complete sentences, which means they are both independent clauses. Independent clauses can only be linked in a few ways, including with a comma plus a coordinating conjunction. This choice uses the coordinating conjunction “and,” but it is missing the comma beforehand. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence error. Both clauses in this sentence could stand alone as complete sentences, which means they are both independent clauses. Independent clauses need to have certain kinds of punctuation marks between them. This choice doesn’t use any punctuation between the two clauses.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "0ed4b07b","Question": "The ﬁne, powdery substance that covers the Moon’s surface is called regolith. Because regolith is both readily available and high in oxygen ______ scientists have wondered whether it could be used as a potential source of oxygen for future lunar settlements. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "content and","B": "content,","C": "content","D": "content, and","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a subordinate clause and a main clause. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the subordinate clause (“Because...content”) and the main clause (“scientists...settlements”). Choice A is incorrect. Joining the subordinate clause (“Because...content”) and the clause that follows (“scientists...settlements”) with the conjunction “and” results in an ungrammatical sentence that lacks a main clause. Choice C is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the subordinate clause and the main clause with appropriate punctuation. Choice D is incorrect. Joining the subordinate clause (“Because...content”) and the clause that follows (“scientists...settlements”) with a comma and the conjunction “and” results in an ungrammatical sentence that lacks a main clause.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "10b9dc53","Question": "The intense pressure found in the deep ocean can affect the structure of proteins in ﬁsh’s cells, distorting the proteins’ shape. The chemical trimethylamine N-oxide (TMAO) counters this effect, ensuring that proteins retain their original ______ is found in high concentrations in the cells of the deepest-dwelling ﬁsh. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "conﬁgurations. TM","B": "conﬁgurations TMAO","C": "conﬁgurations, TMAO","D": "conﬁgurations and TMAO","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period after “conﬁgurations” is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence (“The intense…conﬁgurations”) and another (“TMAO…ﬁsh”). The supplementary phrase (“ensuring…conﬁgurations”) modiﬁes the main clause of the ﬁrst sentence (“The chemical…effect”), and “TMAO” is the subject of the second sentence. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences (“The intense…conﬁgurations” and “TMAO… ﬁsh”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice D is incorrect. Without a comma preceding it, the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to join sentences.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "123676b8","Question": "Swedish scientists Eva Engvall and Peter Perlmann developed a method for measuring the concentration of different proteins in a biological sample. Their ______ ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay), is used to detect and measure proteins that indicate the presence of certain diseases. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "method (called","B": "method—called","C": "method, called","D": "method called","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary element within a sentence. The comma after “method” pairs with the comma after the closing parenthesis to separate the supplementary element “called ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay)” from the rest of the sentence. This supplementary element functions to identify the name of Engvall and Perlmann’s method, and the pair of commas indicates that this element could be removed without affecting the grammatical coherence of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because an opening parenthesis can’t be paired with a comma to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice B is incorrect because a dash can’t be paired with a comma to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice D is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "12cd60b9","Question": "Richard Spikes was a proliﬁc African American inventor known for his contributions to automotive engineering. Between 1907 and 1946, he patented many inventions, ______ an automobile turn signal, a safety brake, and—most famously—the ﬁrst automatic gearshift. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "included","B": "includes","C": "including","D": "will include","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. The nonﬁnite present participle 'including' is correctly used to form a participial phrase that supplements the main clause 'he patented many inventions,' listing several of Spikes’s patented inventions. Choice A is incorrect because the ﬁnite past tense verb 'included' can’t be used in this way to supplement the main clause 'he patented many inventions.' Choice B is incorrect because the ﬁnite present tense verb 'includes' can’t be used in this way to supplement the main clause 'he patented many inventions.' Choice D is incorrect because the ﬁnite future tense verb 'will include' can’t be used in this way to supplement the main clause 'he patented many inventions.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "1621d2b8","Question": "A second-generation Japanese American, Wataru Misaka ______ in World War II (1941-45) and won two amateur national basketball championships at the University of Utah when he joined the New York Knicks for the 1947-48 season, becoming the ﬁrst non-white basketball player in the US’s top professional league. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "already served","B": "was already serving","C": "already serves","D": "had already served","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. Misaka served in World War II before he joined the New York Knicks in 1947. To show that a past occurrence took place before another past occurrence, we need to use “had” + the past tense form of the verb. This is called the past perfect tense. Choice A is incorrect. Misaka served in World War II before he joined the Knicks. Both events are in the past, but his service in World War II happened earlier, so we need a verb that makes it clear that his service (and the two national championships) had ended by the time he joined the Knicks. Choice B is incorrect. “Was already serving” forms the continuous past tense, which we use when we’re showing a past action that was ongoing. Misaka served in World War II before he joined the Knicks. Both events are in the past, but they’re not happening at the same time, so we shouldn’t use the continuous past tense here. Choice C is incorrect. Misaka served in World War II in the past, so we shouldn’t use the present tense “serves.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "1624b82d","Question": "Scientists believe that, unlike most other species of barnacle, turtle barnacles (Chelonibia testudinari) can dissolve the cement-like secretions they use to attach ______ to a sea turtle shell, enabling the barnacles to move short distances across the shell’s surface. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "it","B": "themselves","C": "them","D": "itself","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is pronoun-antecedent agreement. The plural reﬂexive pronoun “themselves” agrees in number with the plural antecedent “turtle barnacles,” correctly indicating what is attached to a sea turtle shell. Choice A is incorrect because the singular pronoun “it” doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent “turtle barnacles.” Choice C is incorrect because it results in an unclear and confusing sentence. In this context, it’s unclear what the plural pronoun “them” refers to. Choice D is incorrect because the singular reﬂexive pronoun “itself” doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent “turtle barnacles.”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "16ec63e6","Question": "Classical composer Florence Price’s 1927 move to Chicago marked a turning point in her career. It was there that Price premiered her First Symphony—a piece that was praised for blending traditional Romantic motifs with aspects of Black folk music—and ______ supportive relationships with other Black artists. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "developing","B": "developed","C": "to develop","D": "having developed","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The missing verb is part of the same clause as the verb 'premiered,' and 'Price' is the subject of both. So we need the past-tense form 'developed' in order to match 'premiered.' Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a verb form error. The missing verb is part of the same clause as the verb 'premiered,' and 'Price' is the subject of both. So we need the past-tense form 'developed' in order to match 'premiered.' Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a verb form error. The missing verb is part of the same clause as the verb 'premiered,' and 'Price' is the subject of both. So we need the past-tense form 'developed' in order to match 'premiered.' Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a verb form error. The missing verb is part of the same clause as the verb 'premiered,' and 'Price' is the subject of both. So we need the past-tense form 'developed' in order to match 'premiered.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "18b215d3","Question": "Journalists have dubbed Gil Scott-Heron the “godfather of rap,” a title that has appeared in hundreds of articles about him since the 1990s. Scott-Heron himself resisted the godfather ______ feeling that it didn’t encapsulate his devotion to the broader African American blues music tradition as well as “bluesologist,” the moniker he preferred. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "nickname, however","B": "nickname, however;","C": "nickname, however,","D": "nickname; however,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between a main clause and two supplementary elements. In this choice, the commas after “nickname” and “however” are correctly used to separate the supplementary adverb “however” from the main clause (“Scott-Heron…nickname”) on one side and the supplementary participial phrase (“feeling…bluesologist”) on the other. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the supplementary adverb “however” and the supplementary phrase (“feeling…bluesologist”). Choice B is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join the supplementary adverb “however” and the supplementary phrase (“feeling…bluesologist”). Choice D is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join the main clause (“Scott-Heron…nickname”) and the supplementary word and phrase (“however” and “feeling…bluesologist”). Moreover, placing the semicolon after “nickname” illogically signals that the following information (Scott-Heron’s feeling that the nickname didn’t encapsulate his devotion to the blues tradition) is contrary to the information in the previous clause (Scott-Heron’s resistance to the nickname).","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "18ccb79a","Question": "About 70,000 meteorites have been found on Earth. Although most meteorites are fragments of ______ hundred have been identiﬁed as being from the Moon or Mars. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "asteroids. Several","B": "asteroids, several","C": "asteroids; several","D": "asteroids: several","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. This choice uses a comma to correctly separate the dependent clause 'although…asteroids' from the independent clause 'several hundred have been…Mars.' Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a sentence fragment. 'Although…asteroids' is a dependent clause. It can’t stand on its own as a sentence, which means it can’t end in a period. Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error. 'Although…asteroids' is a dependent clause and can’t be joined to the independent clause 'several hundred have been… Mars' with a semicolon. A semicolon can only join two independent clauses. Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. A colon can only come after an independent clause, but 'although…asteroids' is a dependent clause.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "19ae9cd4","Question": "In the 1970s, Janaki Ammal, a prominent botanist, emerged as a powerful voice in India’s environmental conservation movement. Her exhaustive chromosomal survey of plants in Silent Valley, a pristine tropical forest in Kerala, India, that is home to nearly 1,000 species of native ﬂora (many of which are endangered), ______ instrumental in the government’s decision to preserve the forest. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "are","B": "were","C": "have been","D": "was","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The subject 'survey' is singular, and so is the verb 'was.' Choice A is incorrect. The subject 'survey' is singular, but the verb 'are' is plural. Choice B is incorrect. The subject 'survey' is singular, but the verb 'were' is plural. Choice C is incorrect. The subject 'survey' is singular, but the verb 'have been' is plural.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "1a633ce1","Question": "In discussing Mary Shelley’s 1818 epistolary novel Frankenstein, literary theorist Gayatri Spivak directs the reader’s attention to the character of Margaret Saville. As Spivak points out, Saville is not the protagonist of Shelley’s ______ as the recipient of the letters that frame the book’s narrative, she’s the “occasion” of it. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "novel","B": "novel,","C": "novel; rather,","D": "novel, rather,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. This choice correctly uses a semicolon to join a main clause (“Saville...novel”) and a second main clause (“she’s...it”) preceded by supplementary elements (“rather...narrative”). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, the comma after “novel” can’t be used in this way to join the two main clauses.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "1b1fd9d2","Question": "To survive when water is scarce, embryos inside African turquoise killiﬁsh eggs ______ a dormant state known as diapause. In this state, embryonic development is paused for as long as two years—longer than the life span of an adult killiﬁsh. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "enter","B": "to enter","C": "having entered","D": "entering","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is ﬁnite and nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. A main clause requires a ﬁnite verb to perform the action of the subject (in this case, “embryos”), and this choice supplies the clause with the ﬁnite present tense verb “enter” to indicate how the embryos achieve diapause. Choice B is incorrect because the nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to enter” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice C is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “having entered” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice D is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “entering” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "1bc66123","Question": "Farouk El-Baz, a geologist and space scientist, ______ part of the team that selected the lunar landing sites for the Apollo program during the 1960s and 1970s. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "are","B": "was","C": "have been","D": "were","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb 'was' agrees in number with the singular subject 'Farouk El-Baz.' Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb 'are' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'Farouk El-Baz.' Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb 'have been' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'Farouk El-Baz.' Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb 'were' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'Farouk El-Baz.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "1c16f0f0","Question": "Based on genetic evidence, archaeologists have generally agreed that reindeer domestication began in the eleventh century CE. However, since uncovering fragments of a 2,000-year-old reindeer training harness in northern Siberia, ______ may have begun much earlier. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "researcher Robert Losey has argued that domestication","B": "researcher Robert Losey’s argument is that domestication","C": "domestication, researcher Robert Losey has argued,","D": "the argument researcher Robert Losey has made is that domestication","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice makes the noun phrase “researcher Robert Losey” the subject of the sentence and places it immediately after the modifying phrase “since…Siberia.” In doing so, this choice clearly establishes that researcher Robert Losey—and not another noun in the sentence—is who uncovered fragments of a 2,000-year-old reindeer training harness in northern Siberia. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “researcher Robert Losey’s argument” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the “argument” is what uncovered fragments of a 2,000-year-old reindeer training harness in northern Siberia. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun “domestication” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that “domestication” is what uncovered fragments of a 2,000-year-old reindeer training harness in northern Siberia. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “the argument” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the “argument” is what uncovered fragments of a 2,000-year-old reindeer training harness in northern Siberia.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "1cd5b06a","Question": "In his 1963 exhibition Exposition of Music—Electronic Television, Korean American artist Nam June Paik showed how television images could be manipulated to express an artist’s perspective. Today, Paik ______ considered the ﬁrst video artist. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "will be","B": "had been","C": "was","D": "is","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense. In this choice, the present tense verb “is,” used in conjunction with the word “today,” correctly indicates that Paik is currently considered the ﬁrst video artist. Choice A is incorrect because the future-indicating verb “will be” doesn’t indicate that Paik is currently considered the ﬁrst video artist. Choice B is incorrect because the past perfect tense verb “had been” doesn’t indicate that Paik is currently considered the ﬁrst video artist. Choice C is incorrect because the past tense verb “was” doesn’t indicate that Paik is currently considered the ﬁrst video artist.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "1d2429ef","Question": "In 1943, in the midst of World War II, mathematics professor Grace Hopper was recruited by the US military to help the war effort by solving complex equations. Hopper’s subsequent career would involve more than just ______ as a pioneering computer programmer, Hopper would help usher in the digital age. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "equations, though:","B": "equations, though,","C": "equations. Though,","D": "equations though","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of punctuation to mark boundaries between supplements and clauses. The comma after “equations” is used to separate the independent clause (“Hopper’s…equation”) from the supplementary adverb phrase “though.” The colon after “though” is used to mark the boundary between the clause ending with “though” and the following clause (“as…age”). A colon used in this way introduces information that illustrates or explains information that has come before it. In this case, the colon after “though” introduces the following explanation of how Hopper’s subsequent career would involve more than just solving equations: she would become a pioneering computer programmer. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to join two independent clauses (“Hopper’s…though” and “as…age”) such as these. Choice C is incorrect because it results in an illogical sequence of sentences. Placing the period after “equations” and beginning the next sentence with “Though” illogically suggests that the following information (that Hopper would help usher in the digital age) is contrary to the information in the previous sentence (Hopper’s subsequent career would involve more than just solving equations). Instead, the information that follows supports the information from the previous sentence by explaining how her work and inﬂuence extended beyond solely solving equations. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two independent clauses (“Hopper’s… though” and “as…age”) are fused without punctuation.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "1d918ae7","Question": "Professional American football player Fred Cox invented one of the world’s most popular toys. In the 1970s, he came up with the idea for the Nerf football, which ______ of the harder and heavier regulation football. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "were a smaller, foam version","B": "are smaller, foam versions","C": "were smaller, foam versions","D": "is a smaller, foam version","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement and agreement between nouns. The singular verb “is” and the singular noun “version” both agree in number with the relative pronoun “which.” In this context, “which” functions as a singular subject because it refers to the singular noun “the Nerf football.” Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb “were” doesn’t agree in number with the singular noun phrase “the Nerf football” that it’s modifying. Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb “are” and the plural noun “versions” don’t agree in number with the singular noun phrase “the Nerf football” that they’re modifying. Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb “were” and the plural noun “versions” don’t agree in number with the singular noun phrase “the Nerf football” that they’re modifying.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "203d871f","Question": "In 2018, a team of researchers led by Dr. Caitlin Whalen compiled every available measurement of ocean mixing rates from the past two decades. With this novel data set, the team was able to determine how current-driven mixing varies across ______ and what impact it has on the distribution of heat and nutrients in the ocean. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "regions,","B": "regions:","C": "regions;","D": "regions","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between coordinates in a sentence. The two elements 'how…regions' and 'what…ocean' work together as coordinates to complete the description of what the team was able to determine. Because there are only two coordinates in this case (as opposed to a series of three or more), no punctuation is needed between them. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the coordinates 'how…regions' and 'what…ocean.' Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the coordinates 'how…regions' and 'what…ocean.' Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the coordinates 'how…regions' and 'what…ocean.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "2254ecf6","Question": "Like other amphibians, the wood frog (Rana sylvatica) is unable to generate its own heat, so during periods of subfreezing temperatures, it ______ by producing large amounts of glucose, a sugar that helps prevent damaging ice from forming inside its cells. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "had survived","B": "survived","C": "would survive","D": "survives","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense. In this choice, the present tense verb “survives” correctly indicates that the wood frog regularly survives subfreezing temperatures by producing large amounts of glucose. Choice A is incorrect because the past perfect verb “had survived” doesn’t indicate that the wood frog regularly survives subfreezing temperatures by producing large amounts of glucose. Choice B is incorrect because the past tense verb “survived” doesn’t indicate that the wood frog regularly survives subfreezing temperatures by producing large amounts of glucose. Choice C is incorrect because the conditional verb “would survive” doesn’t indicate that the wood frog regularly survives subfreezing temperatures by producing large amounts of glucose.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "23507571","Question": "In a 2016 study, Eastern Washington University psychologist Amani El-Alayli found that, among the study participants who experienced frisson (a physiological response akin to goosebumps or getting the chills) while listening to music, there was one personality trait that they scored particularly ______ openness to experience. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "high. On","B": "high on;","C": "high on","D": "high on:","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between a main clause and a supplementary phrase. In this choice, a colon is correctly used to mark the boundary between the main clause ('there...on') and the supplementary phrase ('openness to experience') and to introduce the information that identiﬁes which personality trait participants scored especially high on. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with 'on' and separates a necessary preposition from the clause beginning with 'there.' Choice B is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join the main clause ('there...on') and the supplementary phrase ('openness to experience'). A semicolon is conventionally used to join two main clauses, whereas a colon is conventionally used to introduce an element that explains or ampliﬁes the information in the preceding clause, making the colon the better choice in this context. Choice C is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the main clause ('there...on') and the supplementary phrase ('openness to experience').","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "247072bd","Question": "After the United Kingdom began rolling out taxes equivalent to a few cents on single-use plastic grocery bags in 2011, plastic-bag consumption decreased by up to ninety ______ taxes are subject to what economists call the “rebound effect”: as the change became normalized, plastic-bag use started to creep back up. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "percent, such","B": "percent and such","C": "percent. Such","D": "percent such","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period after “percent” is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence (“After…percent”) and another (“Such…up”). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice B is incorrect. Without a comma preceding it, the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to join sentences. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences (“After…percent” and “Such…up”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "25ad839c","Question": "Far from being modern inventions, ______ more than 5,000 years ago. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Sumerians in ancient Mesopotamia used drinking straws","B": "drinking straws were used by Sumerians in ancient Mesopotamia","C": "the use of drinking straws by Sumerians in ancient Mesopotamia happened","D": "ancient Mesopotamia was home to Sumerians who used drinking straws","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The modiﬁer “far from being modern inventions” must be describing “drinking straws,” because those are the only possible inventions in this sentence. Choice A is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The modiﬁer “far from being modern inventions” can’t be describing “Sumerians,” because they are a group of people, not an invention. Choice C is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The modiﬁer “far from being modern inventions” can’t be describing “the use of drinking straws,” because it is not “the use” of drinking straws that is an invention—it is the drinking straws themselves. Choice D is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The modiﬁer “far from being modern inventions” can’t be describing “Ancient Mesopotamia,” because that is a place, not an invention.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "277edb14","Question": "In winter, the diets of Japanese macaques, also known as snow monkeys, are inﬂuenced more by food availability than by food preference. Although the monkeys prefer to eat vegetation and land-dwelling invertebrates, those food sources may become unavailable because of extensive snow and ice cover, ______ the monkeys to hunt for marine animals in any streams that have not frozen over. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "forces","B": "to force","C": "forcing","D": "forced","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of ﬁnite and nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. The nonﬁnite present participle “forcing” is correctly used to form a participial phrase that supplements the main clause “those...cover,” describing the effects on monkeys of the lack of food sources. Choice A is incorrect because the ﬁnite present tense verb “forces” can’t be used in this way to supplement the main clause (“those...cover”). Choice B is incorrect. While the nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to force” could be used to form a subordinate clause that supplements the main clause (“those...cover”), to-inﬁnitives conventionally express purpose, and nothing in the sentence suggests that the food sources become unavailable for the purpose of forcing monkeys to hunt marine animals. Choice D is incorrect because the ﬁnite past tense verb “forced” can’t be used in this way to supplement the main clause (“those...cover”).","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "293f60f6","Question": "Mathematician and meteorologist Edward Lorenz used the metaphor of the “butterﬂy effect” to explain how seemingly minor events can have major impacts on future weather. According to Lorenz’s metaphor, the wind from a butterﬂy ﬂapping ______ in Brazil might eventually grow into a storm elsewhere across the globe. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "its wings","B": "its wings’","C": "it’s wing’s","D": "it’s wings’","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The conventions being tested are the use of possessive determiners and plural nouns. The singular possessive determiner 'its' and the plural noun 'wings' correctly indicate that the butterﬂy has multiple wings. Choice B is incorrect because the context requires the plural noun 'wings,' not the plural possessive noun 'wings’.' Choice C is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive determiner 'its' and the plural noun 'wings,' not the contraction 'it’s' and the singular possessive noun 'wing’s.' Choice D is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive determiner 'its' and the plural noun 'wings,' not the contraction 'it’s' and the plural possessive noun 'wings’.'","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "29ed3849","Question": "Rabinal Achí is a precolonial Maya dance drama performed annually in Rabinal, a town in the Guatemalan highlands. Based on events that occurred when Rabinal was a city-state ruled by a king, ______ had once been an ally of the king but was later captured while leading an invading force against him. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Rabinal hí tells the story of K’iche’ hí, a military leader who","B": "K’iche’ Achí, the military leader in the story of Rabinal Achí,","C": "the military leader whose story is told in Rabinal Achí, K’iche’ Achí,","D": "there was a military leader, K’iche’ Achí, who in Rabinal Achí","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The modiﬁer “Based on events…by a king,” is describing the drama “Rabinal Achí.” Modiﬁers need to be next to the subjects they describe, so “Rabinal Achí” needs to be the ﬁrst word after the comma. Choice B is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. The modiﬁer “Based on events…by a king,” is describing the drama “Rabinal Achí.” Modiﬁers need to be next to the subjects they describe, so “Rabinal Achí” needs to be the ﬁrst word after the comma. Choice C is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. The modiﬁer “Based on events…by a king,” is describing the drama “Rabinal Achí.” Modiﬁers need to be next to the subjects they describe, so “Rabinal Achí” needs to be the ﬁrst word after the comma. Choice D is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. The modiﬁer “Based on events…by a king,” is describing the drama “Rabinal Achí.” Modiﬁers need to be next to the subjects they describe, so “Rabinal Achí” needs to be the ﬁrst word after the comma.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "2a5f4b85","Question": "Literary agents estimate that more than half of all nonﬁction books credited to a celebrity or other public ﬁgure are in fact written by ghostwriters, professional authors who are paid to write other ______ but whose names never appear on book covers. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "people’s stories","B": "peoples story’s","C": "peoples stories","D": "people’s story’s","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of plural and possessive nouns. The plural possessive noun “people’s” and the plural noun “stories” correctly indicate that there are multiple stories from multiple people. Choice B is incorrect because the context requires the plural possessive noun “people’s” and the plural noun “stories,” not the plural noun “peoples” and the singular possessive noun “story’s.” Choice C is incorrect because the context requires the plural possessive noun “people’s,” not the plural noun “peoples.” Choice D is incorrect because the context requires the plural noun “stories,” not the singular possessive noun “story’s.”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "2a9b1398","Question": "In 1966, Emmett Ashford became the ﬁrst African American to umpire a Major League Baseball game. His energetic gestures announcing when a player had struck out and his habit of barreling after a hit ball to see if it would land out of ______ transform the traditionally solemn umpire role into a dynamic one. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "bounds helped","B": "bounds, helping","C": "bounds that helped","D": "bounds to help","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is ﬁnite verb use in a main clause. A main clause requires a ﬁnite verb to perform the action of the subject (in this case, Ashford’s “gestures” and “habit”), and this choice supplies the ﬁnite past tense verb “helped” to indicate what Ashford’s gestures and habit helped accomplish. Choice B is incorrect because the non-ﬁnite participle “helping” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice C is incorrect because the relative clause “that helped” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice D is incorrect because the non-ﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to help” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "2c88d54a","Question": "In 2010, archaeologist Noel Hidalgo Tan was visiting the twelfth-century temple of Angkor Wat in Cambodia when he noticed markings of red paint on the temple ______ the help of digital imaging techniques, he discovered the markings to be part of an elaborate mural containing over 200 paintings. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "walls, with","B": "walls with","C": "walls so with","D": "walls. With","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period after “walls” is used correctly to mark the boundary between the ﬁrst sentence (“In...walls”) and the second sentence (“With… techniques”), which starts with a supplementary phrase. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences (“In...walls” and “with...paintings”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice C is incorrect. Without a comma preceding it, the conjunction “so” can’t be used in this way to join sentences.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "2c9fab67","Question": "Both Sona Charaipotra, an Indian American, and Dhonielle Clayton, an African American, grew up frustrated by the lack of diverse characters in books for young people. In 2011, these two writers joined forces to found CAKE Literary, a book packaging ______ specializes in the creation and promotion of stories told from diverse perspectives for children and young adults. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "company,","B": "company that","C": "company","D": "company, that","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use and punctuation of an integrated relative clause. This choice correctly uses the relative pronoun “that” and no punctuation to create an integrated relative clause that provides essential information about the noun phrase (“a book packaging company”) that it modiﬁes. Choice A is incorrect because it doesn’t use a relative pronoun to link the verb phrase beginning with “specializes” to the noun phrase that it modiﬁes (“a book packaging company”). Choice C is incorrect because it doesn’t use a relative pronoun to link the verb phrase beginning with “specializes” to the noun phrase that it modiﬁes (“a book packaging company”). Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the integrated relative clause beginning with “that specializes” and the noun phrase that it modiﬁes (“a book packaging company”).","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "2d2412d1","Question": "The Mission 66 initiative, which was approved by Congress in 1956, represented a major investment in the infrastructure of overburdened national ______ it prioritized physical improvements to the parks’ roads, utilities, employee housing, and visitor facilities while also establishing educational programming for the public. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "parks and","B": "parks","C": "parks;","D": "parks,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. This choice uses a semicolon to correctly join the ﬁrst main clause (“The Mission…parks”) and the second main clause that begins with “it.” Choice A is incorrect. When coordinating two longer main clauses such as these, it’s conventional to use a comma before the coordinating conjunction. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "2e15b3d6","Question": "After immigrating from Mexico and obtaining U.S. citizenship, Octaviano Ambrosio Larrazolo entered politics, earning a reputation for being a fervent defender of Hispanic civil rights. In 1919 Larrazolo was elected governor of ______ in 1928 he became the nation’s ﬁrst Hispanic U.S. Senator. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "New Mexico and","B": "New Mexico,","C": "New Mexico, and","D": "New Mexico","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. This choice correctly uses a comma and the coordinating conjunction 'and' to join the ﬁrst main clause ('In 1919 Larrazolo was elected governor of New Mexico') and the second main clause ('in 1928 he became the nation’s ﬁrst Hispanic US Senator'). Choice A is incorrect because when coordinating two longer main clauses such as these, it’s conventional to use a comma before the coordinating conjunction. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "2ed74e51","Question": "Smaller than poppy seeds, tardigrades are tiny, but they are tough. These minuscule animals can survive for thirty years without food or water, and ______ can withstand extreme temperatures as low as minus 328 degrees and as high as 304 degrees Fahrenheit. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "that","B": "it","C": "they","D": "he","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is pronoun-antecedent agreement. The plural pronoun 'they' agrees in number with the plural antecedent 'animals,' which refers to tardigrades. Choice A is incorrect because the singular pronoun 'that' doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent 'animals.' Choice B is incorrect because the singular pronoun 'it' doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent 'animals.' Choice D is incorrect because the singular pronoun 'he' doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent 'animals.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "310f9117","Question": "Cheng Dang and her colleagues at the University of Washington recently ran simulations to determine the extent to which individual snow ______ affect the amount of light reﬂecting off a snowy surface. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "grain’s physical properties’","B": "grains’ physical properties","C": "grains’ physical property’s","D": "grains physical properties","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of plural and possessive nouns. The plural possessive noun “grains’” and the plural noun “properties” correctly indicate that the simulations involved multiple snow grains and that those snow grains had several properties. Choice A is incorrect because the context requires the plural possessive noun “grains’” and the plural noun “properties,” not the singular possessive noun “grain’s” and the plural possessive noun “properties’.” Choice C is incorrect because the context requires the plural noun “properties,” not the singular possessive noun “property’s.” Choice D is incorrect because the context requires the plural possessive noun “grains’,” not the plural noun “grains.”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "3282352e","Question": "American poet Emily Dickinson wrote many of her poems on scraps of paper, but she also took steps to collect these works. From 1858 to around 1864, for example, she copied more than 800 of ______ into forty homemade booklets (known as fascicles). Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "them","B": "this","C": "that","D": "it","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The pronoun 'them' agrees with the plural antecedents 'poems' and 'works.' Choice B is incorrect. 'This' is a singular pronoun, but its antecedents, 'poems' and 'works,' are plural. Choice C is incorrect. 'That' is a singular pronoun, but its antecedents, 'poems' and 'works,' are plural. Choice D is incorrect. 'It' is a singular pronoun, but its antecedents, 'poems' and 'works,' are plural.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "333f846b","Question": "The 2022 Nobel Prize in Chemistry was awarded to three pioneers in the ﬁeld of click chemistry: two-time Nobel laureate Barry Sharpless, who coined the term “click chemistry” in 1998; Carolyn Bertozzi, founder of the Bertozzi Group at ______ and Morten Meldal, a professor at the University of Copenhagen in Denmark. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Stanford","B": "Stanford,","C": "Stanford:","D": "Stanford;","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. This choice correctly uses a semicolon to punctuate a complex list (which is made up of items that have commas in them). Choice A is incorrect. This is a complex list, indicated by the semicolon between '1998' and 'Carolyn Bertozzi.' What comes after the blank is a separate list item, so punctuation is needed after 'Stanford.' Choice B is incorrect. This is a complex list, indicated by the semicolon between '1998' and 'Carolyn Bertozzi.' The items in this list have internal punctuation in the form of commas and must therefore be separated by semicolons to avoid confusion. Choice C is incorrect. This is a complex list, indicated by the semicolon between '1998' and 'Carolyn Bertozzi.' Colons aren’t used to separate items in a list.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "34fdbf1b","Question": "The ﬁeld of geological oceanography owes much to American ______ Marie Tharp, a pioneering oceanographic cartographer whose detailed topographical maps of the ocean ﬂoor and its multiple rift valleys helped garner acceptance for the theories of plate tectonics and continental drift. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "geologist,","B": "geologist","C": "geologist;","D": "geologist:","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. “Marie tharp” is essential information that completes the ﬁrst clause — the ﬁrst clause doesn’t function without it. So we don’t want to separate it with punctuation. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. “The ﬁeld of geological oceanography owes much to American geologist” is unclear: which geologist are we talking about? We need the “Marie Tharp” for clarity, which means it’s essential information and should not be separated by a comma. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. “The ﬁeld of geological oceanography owes much to American geologist” is unclear: which geologist are we talking about? We need the “Marie Tharp” for clarity, which means it’s essential information and should not be separated by a semicolon. Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. “The ﬁeld of geological oceanography owes much to American geologist” is unclear: which geologist are we talking about? We need the “Marie Tharp” for clarity, which means it’s essential information and should not be separated by a colon.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "355670a5","Question": "Emperor penguins don’t waddle out of the ocean. They launch themselves at such a high speed that they travel up to two meters before landing. How ______ A layer of microbubbles on their plumage reduces friction as the penguins speed to the surface. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "they are able to move so fast!","B": "are they able to move so fast.","C": "they are able to move so fast.","D": "are they able to move so fast?","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is end-of-sentence punctuation. This choice correctly uses a question mark to punctuate the interrogative sentence “how are they able to move so fast?” The interrogative sentence asks a direct question, and the next sentence answers it. Choice A is incorrect because the context requires an interrogative sentence. The exclamative sentence “how they are able to move so fast!” emphasizes the penguin’s high rate of speed, but it doesn’t set up the next sentence’s explanation of how the penguins achieve such speeds. Choice B is incorrect because a period can’t be used in this way to punctuate an interrogative sentence. Choice C is incorrect because the context requires an interrogative sentence. The exclamative sentence “how they are able to move so fast” emphasizes the penguin’s high rate of speed, but it doesn’t set up the next sentence’s explanation of how the penguins achieve such speeds.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "36b27e4c","Question": "In the historical novel The Surrender Tree, Cuban American author Margarita Engle uses poetry rather than prose ______ the true story of Cuban folk hero Rosa La Bayamesa. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "tells","B": "told","C": "is telling","D": "to tell","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of ﬁnite and nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. The nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to tell” is correctly used to form a nonﬁnite (inﬁnitive) clause that explains the reason Engle uses poetry in her novel. Choice A is incorrect because the ﬁnite present tense verb “tells” can’t be used in this way to explain the reason that Engle uses poetry in her novel. Choice B is incorrect because the ﬁnite past tense verb “told” can’t be used in this way to explain the reason that Engle uses poetry in her novel. Choice C is incorrect because the ﬁnite present progressive tense verb “is telling” can’t be used in this way to explain the reason that Engle uses poetry in her novel.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "38a94ca9","Question": "As British scientist Peter Whibberley has observed, “the Earth is not a very good timekeeper.” Earth’s slightly irregular rotation rate means that measurements of time must be periodically adjusted. Speciﬁcally, an extra “leap second” (the 86,401st second of the day) is ______ time based on the planet’s rotation lags a full nine-tenths of a second behind time kept by precise atomic clocks. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "added, whenever","B": "added; whenever","C": "added. Whenever","D": "added whenever","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a verb and a preposition. When, as in this case, a verb (“is added”) is immediately followed by a preposition (“whenever”), no punctuation is needed. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and the preposition. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and the preposition. Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and the preposition.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "3953002d","Question": "Generations of mystery and horror ______ have been inﬂuenced by the dark, gothic stories of celebrated American author Edgar Allan Poe (1809–1849). Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "writers","B": "writers,","C": "writers—","D": "writers;","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a subject and a verb. When, as in this case, a subject (“Generations of mystery and horror writers”) is immediately followed by a verb (“have been inﬂuenced”), no punctuation is needed. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "3a8c00d0","Question": "Hegra is an archaeological site in present-day Saudi Arabia and was the second largest city of the Nabataean Kingdom (fourth century BCE to ﬁrst century CE). Archaeologist Laila Nehmé recently traveled to Hegra to study its ancient ______ into the rocky outcrops of a vast desert, these burial chambers seem to blend seamlessly with nature. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "tombs. Built","B": "tombs, built","C": "tombs and built","D": "tombs built","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period after “tombs” is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence (“Archaeologist...tombs”) and another (“Built...nature”). Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice C is incorrect. Without a comma preceding it, the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to join the two sentences. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences (“Archaeologist...tombs” and “Built...nature”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "3c321e41","Question": "Seneca sculptor Marie Watt’s blanket art comes in a range of shapes and sizes. In 2004, Watt sewed strips of blankets together to craft a 10-by-13-inch ______ in 2014, she arranged folded blankets into two large stacks and then cast them in bronze, creating two curving 18-foot-tall blue-bronze pillars. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "sampler later,","B": "sampler;","C": "sampler,","D": "sampler, later,","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. This choice uses a semicolon in a conventional way to join the ﬁrst main clause (“In 2004…sampler”) and the second main clause (“in 2014…pillars”). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses. The word “later” is an adverb and cannot be used to join two main clauses unless it is preceded by a conjunction. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses. The word “later” is an adverb and cannot be used to join two main clauses unless it is preceded by a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "3ff92750","Question": "It is generally true that technological change is a linear process, in which once-useful technologies are replaced by new and better ______ the reawakening of interest in the steam engine (from advocates of carbon-neutral rail travel) reminds us that ostensibly obsolete technologies may be brought back into service to address society’s changing needs. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "ones, even so;","B": "ones even so,","C": "ones; even so,","D": "ones, even so,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. This choice uses a semicolon in a conventional way to join the ﬁrst main clause (“It is…ones”) and the second main clause (“even so… needs”). Furthermore, the placement of the semicolon after “ones” indicates that the supplementary phrase “even so” modiﬁes the following clause (“the reawakening...needs”), resulting in the most logical and grammatically complete sentence. With this punctuation, the sentence logically indicates that the recent interest in an old technology like steam engines is despite the fact that technological change typically seeks out new technologies. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a confusing and illogical sentence. Placing the semicolon after “so” indicates that the supplementary element “even so” modiﬁes the ﬁrst clause of the sentence, which doesn’t make sense in this context. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. It fails to mark the boundary between the two main clauses with appropriate punctuation. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join the two main clauses of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "405401eb","Question": "For thousands of years, people in the Americas ______ the bottle gourd, a large bitter fruit with a thick rind, to make bottles, other types of containers, and even musical instruments. Oddly, there is no evidence that any type of bottle gourd is native to the Western Hemisphere; either the fruit or its seeds must have somehow been carried from Asia or Africa. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "to use","B": "have used","C": "having used","D": "using","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is ﬁnite and nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. A main clause requires a ﬁnite verb to perform the action of the subject (in this case, “people in the Americas”), and this choice supplies the ﬁnite past perfect tense verb “have used” to indicate what people in the Americas used the gourd for. Choice A is incorrect because the nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to use” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice C is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “having used” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice D is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “using” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "415e7b3d","Question": "Nine months before Rosa Parks made history by refusing to comply with the segregated seating policy on a Montgomery, Alabama, bus, a ﬁfteen-year-old Montgomery girl named Claudette Colvin was arrested for the same ______ to some historians, Colvin’s arrest led to Parks’s action and eventually to the desegregation of Montgomery’s bus system. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "offense. cording","B": "offense, according","C": "offense according","D": "offense and according","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. “Nine months…offense” and “according to…system” are both independent clauses. Separating them with a period and turning them into their own sentences is the only grammatically correct choice among the provided options. Choice B is incorrect. This choice results in a comma splice error, which is a punctuation error that occurs when two independent clauses are joined by only a comma. “Nine months…offense” and “according to…system” are both independent clauses, so they need to be either joined by a semicolon, joined by a comma and a coordinating conjunction, or separated by a period. Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence, which occurs when two independent clauses are joined without punctuation. “Nine months…offense” and “according to…system” are both independent clauses, so they need to be either joined by a semicolon, joined by a comma and a coordinating conjunction, or separated by a period. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence, which occurs when two independent clauses are joined without punctuation. “Nine months…offense” and “according to…system” are independent clauses, so we would need to put a comma before the coordinating conjunction “and” to join them properly.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "41f2da4f","Question": "The US Geological Survey wants to map every human-made structure in the United States, and it is asking volunteers to help. Cassie Tammy Wang and Ashish D’Souza are just two of the many volunteer map editors who ______ to the project since it began in 2012. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "contribute","B": "will contribute","C": "have contributed","D": "will be contributing","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense in a sentence. In this choice, the present perfect tense verb “have contributed,” used in conjunction with the phrase “since it began in 2012,” correctly indicates that map editors have contributed in the past and continue to do so in the present. Choice A is incorrect because the present tense verb “contribute” is inconsistent with the phrase “since it began in 2012,” which suggests that the contributions occurred in the past and continue into the present. Choice B is incorrect because the future tense verb “will contribute” is inconsistent with the phrase “since it began in 2012,” which suggests that the contributions occurred in the past and continue into the present. Choice D is incorrect because the future tense verb “will be contributing” is inconsistent with the phrase “since it began in 2012,” which suggests that the contributions occurred in the past and continue into the present.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "4317ee4a","Question": "In Death Valley National Park’s Racetrack Playa, a ﬂat, dry lakebed, are 162 rocks—some weighing less than a pound but others almost 700 pounds—that move periodically from place to place, seemingly of their own volition. Racetrack-like trails in the ______ mysterious migration. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "playas sediment mark the rock’s","B": "playa’s sediment mark the rocks","C": "playa’s sediment mark the rocks’","D": "playas’ sediment mark the rocks’","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of plural and possessive nouns. The singular possessive noun “playa’s” and the plural possessive noun “rocks’” correctly indicate that the sediment is that of one playa (the Racetrack Playa) and that there are multiple rocks that have mysteriously migrated across the sediment. Choice A is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive noun “playa’s” and the plural possessive noun “rocks’,” not the plural noun “playas” and the singular possessive noun “rock’s.” Choice B is incorrect because the context requires the plural possessive noun “rocks’,” not the plural noun “rocks.” Choice D is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive noun “playa’s,” not the plural possessive noun “playas’.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "43443a3f","Question": "Santa Clara Pueblo artist Roxanne Swentzell’s sculpture Mud Woman Rolls On consists of ﬁve human ﬁgures made of clay and plant ﬁber and arranged in descending size; each ﬁgure holds the smaller one in front of it. The arrangement of the ﬁgures, according to ______ represents her idea that “we all come from the Earth, generation after generation.” Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Swentzell","B": "Swentzell,","C": "Swentzell:","D": "Swentzell—","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The phrase “according to Swentzell” is an aside that interrupts the ﬂow of the sentence, so it needs to be separated from the sentence with a pair of matching punctuation marks: two commas, two dashes, or a pair of parentheses. We already have a comma before “according,” so we must add a comma after “Swentzell.” . Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. The phrase “according to Swentzell” is an aside that interrupts the ﬂow of the sentence, so it needs to be separated from the sentence with a pair of matching punctuation marks: one before and one after the phrase. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. “The arrangement of the ﬁgures, according to Swentzell” is not an independent clause, so it can’t come before a colon. Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. The phrase “according to Swentzell” is an aside that interrupts the ﬂow of the sentence, so it needs to be separated from the sentence with a pair of matching punctuation marks. We already have a comma at the beginning, so we have to use another comma here to match. We can’t just switch to a dash! .","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "43e5e8ba","Question": "A standard Argo ﬂoat, a type of autonomous robot, measures temperature and salinity in the upper regions of ice-free oceans. More advanced ﬂoats can measure a wider range of ______ and monitor seasonal ice zones. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "variables: travel to greater depths","B": "variables, travel to greater depths,","C": "variables travel to greater depths,","D": "variables, travel to greater depths;","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of items in a series. The comma after “variables” is used conventionally to separate the ﬁrst and second items in the series, and the comma after “depths” is used conventionally to separate the second and third items. Choice A is incorrect because a colon can’t be used in this way to separate items in a simple series. Choice C is incorrect because a comma is needed after “variables” to separate the ﬁrst and second items in the series. Choice D is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to separate items in a simple series.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "4a6c2336","Question": "In her two major series “Memory Test” and “Autobiography,” painter Howardena Pindell explored themes ______ healing, self- discovery, and memory by cutting and sewing back together pieces of canvas and inserting personal artifacts, such as postcards, into some of the paintings. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "of","B": "of,","C": "of—","D": "of:","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a preposition and its complement. No punctuation is needed between the preposition “of” and its complement, the noun phrase “healing, self-discovery, and memory.” Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between a preposition and its complement. Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between a preposition and its complement. Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between a preposition and its complement.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "4c3a6732","Question": "Oﬃcial measurements of the Mississippi River’s length vary: according to the US Geologic Survey, the river is 2,300 miles long, whereas the Environmental Protection Agency records its length as 2,320 miles. This disparity can be explained in part by the fact that rivers such as the Mississippi expand and contract as ______ sediment. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "they accumulate","B": "one accumulates","C": "it accumulates","D": "we accumulate","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The noun that goes with 'expand and contract' is 'rivers,' a plural noun. 'They' is a third-person plural pronoun, so it can correctly stand in for 'rivers.' Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a pronoun-antecedent agreement error. 'One' is a singular pronoun, but the noun that goes with 'expand and contract' is 'rivers,' a plural noun. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a pronoun- antecedent agreement error. 'It' is a singular pronoun, but the noun that goes with 'expand and contract' is 'rivers,' a plural noun. Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a pronoun-antecedent agreement error. The noun that goes with 'expand and contract' is the plural noun 'rivers.' Rivers are not people, so 'we' can’t be used to stand in for it.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "4e4a780c","Question": "Photosynthesis, the mechanism by which plants use sunlight to turn carbon dioxide and water into ______ is fueled in part by an enzyme called Photosystem II that harvests energy-giving electrons from water molecules. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "nutrients","B": "nutrients and","C": "nutrients,","D": "nutrients—","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary element within a sentence. The comma after “nutrients” pairs with the comma after “photosynthesis” to separate the supplementary element “the mechanism by which plants use sunlight to turn carbon dioxide and water into nutrients” from the rest of the sentence. This supplementary element functions to deﬁne the term “photosynthesis,” and the pair of commas indicates that this element could be removed without affecting the grammatical coherence of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice B is incorrect because a conjunction can’t be paired with a comma in this way to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice D is incorrect because a dash can’t be paired with a comma in this way to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "4f06deb0","Question": "Photographer Ansel Adams’s landscape portraits are iconic pieces of American art. However, many of the ______ of landscapes were intended not as art but as marketing; a concessions company at Yosemite National Park had hired Adams to take pictures of the park for restaurant menus and brochures. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "photographer’s early photo’s","B": "photographers early photo’s","C": "photographer’s early photos","D": "photographers early photos","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. There’s only one photographer (Adams), and the photos are his, so the singular possessive 'photographer’s' is correct. There’s more than one photo, and nothing belongs to the photos, so the simple plural 'photos' is correct. Choice A is incorrect. This choice uses the singular possessive 'photo’s,' which isn’t correct. There’s more than one photo, and they don’t possess anything, so the noun should be the simple plural 'photos.' Choice B is incorrect. This choice uses the simple plural 'photographers' and the singular possessive 'photo’s,' which aren’t correct. There’s only one photographer (Adams) and there’s more than one photo. Choice D is incorrect. This choice uses the simple plural 'photographers,' which isn’t correct. There’s only one photographer (Adams).","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "53b7e7cd","Question": "The city of Pompeii, which was buried in ash following the eruption of Mount Vesuvius in 79 CE, continues to be studied by archaeologists. Unfortunately, as ______ attest, archaeological excavations have disrupted ash deposits at the site, causing valuable information about the eruption to be lost. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "researchers, Roberto Scandone and Christopher Kilburn,","B": "researchers, Roberto Scandone and Christopher Kilburn","C": "researchers Roberto Scandone and ristopher Kilburn","D": "researchers Roberto Scandone, and Christopher Kilburn","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a restrictive coordinated noun phrase. No punctuation is needed within or around the coordinated noun phrase “researchers Roberto Scandone and Christopher Kilburn” because it would create an illogical separation between the noun “researchers” and the coordinated noun phrase “Roberto Scandone and Christopher Kilburn.” Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed. Placing a pair of commas around the coordinated noun phrase “Roberto Scandone and Christopher Kilburn” creates an illogical separation between the noun “researchers” and the aforementioned coordinated noun phrase. In this case, it illogically suggests that researchers in general bear the speciﬁc names Roberto Scandone and Christopher Kilburn. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the noun “researchers” and the coordinated noun phrase “Roberto Scandone and Christopher Kilburn.” Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed within the coordinated noun phrase “Roberto Scandone and Christopher Kilburn.”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "55258d1e","Question": "A model created by biologist Luis Valente predicts that the rate of speciation—the rate at which new species form—on an isolated island located approximately 5,000 kilometers from the nearest mainland ______ triple the rate of speciation on an island only 500 kilometers from the mainland. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "being","B": "to be","C": "to have been","D": "will be","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is ﬁnite and nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. Relative clauses, such as the one beginning with “that,” require a ﬁnite verb, a verb that can function as the main verb of a clause. This choice correctly supplies the clause with the ﬁnite future tense verb “will be.” Choice A is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “being” doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice B is incorrect because the nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to be” doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice C is incorrect because the nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to have been” doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "5542638c","Question": "Occupying a signiﬁcant part of modern-day Nigeria, the Kingdom of Benin was one of the major powers in West Africa between the thirteenth and nineteenth centuries. It ______ ruled by Oba Ewuare I from 1440 to 1473. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "is","B": "will be","C": "has been","D": "was","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense in a sentence. In this choice, the past tense verb “was ruled” correctly indicates that Oba Ewuare I ruled the Kingdom of Benin in the distant past (from 1440 to 1473). This past tense verb choice is consistent with the other past tense verb (“was”) used to describe the Kingdom of Benin. Choice A is incorrect because the present tense verb “is ruled” doesn’t indicate that Oba Ewuare I ruled the Kingdom of Benin in the distant past. Choice B is incorrect because the future tense verb “will be ruled” doesn’t indicate that Oba Ewuare I ruled the Kingdom of Benin in the distant past. Choice C is incorrect because the present perfect tense verb “has been ruled” doesn’t indicate that Oba Ewuare I ruled the Kingdom of Benin in the distant past.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "558700f2","Question": "In recent years, economists around the world have created new tools that quantify the overall well-being of a country’s citizens. Economists in India, for example, use an Ease of Living Index. This tool ______ economic potential, sustainability, and citizens’ quality of life. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "measures","B": "had measured","C": "would have measured","D": "will have been measuring","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The previous sentence tells us how economists in India 'use' a certain tool, while this sentence describes general facts about that tool. To express general facts (and also to match the simple present tense of 'use'), we should use the simple present tense form 'measures.' Choice B is incorrect. This choice uses the past perfect tense, but the previous sentence tells us that the tool is currently used to measure things, so the past tense doesn’t make sense for this verb. Choice C is incorrect. This choice uses the future perfect conditional tense, but the previous sentence tells us that the tool is currently used to measure things, so the future tense doesn’t make sense for this verb. Choice D is incorrect. This choice uses the future perfect continuous tense, but the previous sentence tells us that the tool is currently used to measure things, so the future tense doesn’t make sense for this verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "559624fe","Question": "Midway through her 1968 jazz album A Monastic Trio, Alice Coltrane switches instruments, swapping the piano for the harp. With the same ﬂuid style that Coltrane was famous for on piano, she ______ her ﬁngers across the harp strings and creates a radiant sound. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "sweep","B": "are sweeping","C": "were sweeping","D": "sweeps","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb 'sweeps' agrees in number with the singular subject 'she,' which refers to Alice Coltrane. Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb 'sweep' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'she.' Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb 'are sweeping' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'she.' Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb 'were sweeping' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'she.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "55c8d2b2","Question": "After the printing press was introduced in 1440, handwritten manuscripts from Europe’s medieval period were often destroyed and the paper used for other purposes. In one instance, pages ______ a collection of Norse tales dating to 1270 were discovered lining a bishop’s miter (hat). Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "from:","B": "from,","C": "from","D": "from—","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The word “from” introduces a prepositional phrase that modiﬁes the noun “pages” and provides essential information about their origin. No additional punctuation is needed after “from” in this context. Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error, illogically separating the preposition “from” from the rest of the prepositional phrase with a colon. Also, a colon can only follow an independent clause, but what comes before the blank could not stand on its own as a complete sentence. Choice B is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error, illogically separating the preposition “from” from the rest of the prepositional phrase with a comma. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error, illogically separating the preposition “from” from the rest of the prepositional phrase with a dash.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "567aa03d","Question": "In 1937, Chinese American screen actor Anna May Wong, who had portrayed numerous villains and secondary characters but never a heroine, ﬁnally got a starring role in Paramount Pictures’ Daughter of Shanghai, a ﬁlm that ______ “expanded the range of possibilities for Asian images on screen.” Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "critic, Stina Chyn, claims","B": "critic, Stina Chyn, claims,","C": "critic Stina yn claims","D": "critic Stina Chyn, claims,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The conventions being tested are punctuation use between titles and proper nouns and between verbs and integrated quotations. No punctuation is needed to set off the proper noun “Stina Chyn” from the title that describes Chyn, “critic.” Because “Stina Chyn” is essential information identifying the “critic,” no punctuation is necessary. Further, no punctuation is needed between the verb “claims” and the following quotation because the quotation is integrated into the structure of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed before or after the proper noun “Stina Chyn.” Setting the critic’s name off with commas suggests that it could be removed without affecting the coherence of the sentence, which isn’t the case. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed before or after the proper noun “Stina Chyn.” Setting the critic’s name off with commas suggests that it could be removed without affecting the coherence of the sentence, which isn’t the case. Additionally, no punctuation is needed between “claims” and the integrated quotation. Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb “claims” and its subject, “critic Stina Chyn.” Additionally, no punctuation is needed between the verb “claims” and the integrated quotation.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "578ba226","Question": "The artistic talents of Barbara Chase-Riboud, most known for her 1979 historical novel Sally Hemings and the conversation it inspired, ______ limited to the realm of prose: she ﬁrst excelled in sculpture, where her aﬃnity for bronze—a material she described as “timeless” due to its use across eras and cultures—became part of her artistic identity. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "hasn’t been","B": "wasn’t","C": "isn’t","D": "aren’t","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The subject 'talents' is plural, and so is the verb 'aren’t': 'the artistic talents…aren’t limited.' Choice A is incorrect. The subject 'talents' is plural, but the verb 'hasn’t been' is singular. Choice B is incorrect. The subject 'talents' is plural, but the verb 'wasn’t' is singular. Choice C is incorrect. The subject 'talents' is plural, but the verb 'isn’t' is singular.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "598b42f3","Question": "Over twenty years ago, in a landmark experiment in the psychology of choice, professor Sheena Iyengar set up a jam-tasting booth at a grocery store. The number of jams available for tasting ______ some shoppers had twenty-four different options, others only six. Interestingly, the shoppers with fewer jams to choose from purchased more jam. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "varied:","B": "varied,","C": "varied, while","D": "varied while","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of a colon within a sentence. In this choice, the colon is used in a conventional way to introduce the following description of how the number of jams available varied. Choice B is incorrect because it creates a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses (“the number…varied” and “some…six”). Choice C is incorrect because it results in an illogical and confusing sentence. Using the conjunction “while” to join the main clause (“the number…varied”) with the following clause’s description of the number of jams available suggests that the variation in the number of jams is in contrast to some shoppers having twenty-four options. Choice D is incorrect because it results in an illogical and confusing sentence. Using “while” in this way suggests that the number of jams available varied during the time in which some shoppers had twenty-four options and others had six. The sentence makes clear, however, that what follows “varied” is a description of the variation, not a separate, simultaneous occurrence.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "59b92ac2","Question": "In 1990, California native and researcher Ellen Ochoa left her position as chief of the Intelligent Systems Technology Branch at a NASA research center ______ the space agency’s astronaut training program. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "to join","B": "is joining","C": "joined","D": "joins","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of nonﬁnite verb forms in a sentence. The nonﬁnite to- inﬁnitive verb 'to join' is correctly used to form a subordinate clause that expresses why Ochoa left her position (to join the training program). Choice B is incorrect because the ﬁnite verb 'is joining' can’t be used in this way to indicate Ochoa’s action of joining the training program. A conjunction such as 'and' would be needed to coordinate 'is joining' with the previous ﬁnite verb, 'left.' Choice C is incorrect because the ﬁnite verb 'joined' can’t be used in this way to indicate Ochoa’s action of joining the training program. A conjunction such as 'and' would be needed to coordinate 'joined' with the previous ﬁnite verb, 'left.' Choice D is incorrect because the ﬁnite verb 'joins' can’t be used in this way to indicate Ochoa’s action of joining the training program. A conjunction such as 'and' would be needed to coordinate 'joins' with the previous ﬁnite verb, 'left.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "59c4d9d8","Question": "At eight paragraphs long, the preamble to the constitution of ______ country in Western Asia—is much longer than the one- paragraph preamble to the United States Constitution. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Bahrain—a","B": "hrain, a","C": "Bahrain a","D": "Bahrain: a","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary element within a sentence. The dash after “Bahrain” pairs with the dash after “Asia” to separate the supplementary element “a country in Western Asia” from the rest of the sentence. Choice B is incorrect because a comma can’t be paired with a dash in this way to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice C is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice D is incorrect because a colon can’t be paired with a dash in this way to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "59ef921b","Question": "In the 1950s, a man named Joseph McVicker was struggling to keep his business aﬂoat when his sister-in-law Kay Zufall advised him to repurpose the company’s product, a nontoxic, clay-like substance for removing soot from wallpaper, as a modeling putty for kids. In addition, Zufall ______ selling the product under a child-friendly name: Play-Doh. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "suggested","B": "suggests","C": "had suggested","D": "was suggesting","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense. In this choice, the simple past tense verb “suggested” properly indicates that Zufall offered her suggestion for the product’s name in the past. This verb tense is consistent with the previous sentence’s use of a simple past tense verb (“advised”) to describe Zufall’s advice to McVicker in the 1950s. Choice B is incorrect because the present tense verb “suggests” doesn’t indicate that Zufall offered her suggestion in the past. Choice C is incorrect because the past perfect verb “had suggested” isn’t consistent with the previous sentence’s use of the simple past tense verb “advised” to describe Zufall’s advice to McVicker. Choice D is incorrect because the past progressive verb “was suggesting” isn’t consistent with the previous sentence’s use of the simple past tense verb “advised” to describe Zufall’s advice to McVicker.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "5a8ec3d6","Question": "Joshua Hinson, director of the language revitalization program of the Chickasaw Nation in Oklahoma, helped produce the world’s ﬁrst Indigenous-language instructional app, Chickasaw ______ Chickasaw TV, in 2010; and a Rosetta Stone language course in Chickasaw, in 2015. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Basic; in 2009, an online television network;","B": "sic; in 2009, an online television network,","C": "Basic, in 2009; an online television network,","D": "Basic, in 2009, an online television network,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of items in a complex series. It’s conventional to use a semicolon to separate items in a complex series with internal punctuation, and in this choice, the semicolon after “2009” is conventionally used to separate the ﬁrst item (“the world’s…2009”) and the second item (“an online…2010”) in the series of things that Hinson helped create. Further, the comma after “Basic” correctly pairs with the comma after “app,” and the comma after “network” correctly pairs with the comma after “TV” to set off the supplemental elements (“Chickasaw Basic” and “Chickasaw TV”) that provide the names of the app and the TV network, respectively. Altogether, the punctuation in this choice results in a sentence that clearly indicates that Hinson helped make a language app in 2009, an online TV network in 2010, and a language course in 2015. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to punctuate the complex series in a way that makes clear that Hinson helped make a language app in 2009, an online TV network in 2010, and a language course in 2015. Choice B is incorrect because it fails to punctuate the complex series in a way that makes clear that Hinson helped make a language app in 2009, an online TV network in 2010, and a language course in 2015. Choice D is incorrect because the comma after “2009” doesn’t match the semicolon used to separate the second and third items in the complex series.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "5f302b90","Question": "Typically, underlines, scribbles, and notes left in the margins by a former owner lower a book’s ______ when the former owner is a famous poet like Walt Whitman, such markings, known as marginalia, can be a gold mine to literary scholars. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "value, but","B": "value","C": "value,","D": "value but","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of independent clauses within a sentence. An independent clause is a phrase containing a subject and a verb that can stand on its own as a sentence. This choice uses a comma and the coordinating conjunction “but” to join the ﬁrst independent clause (“underlines…lower a book’s value”) and the second independent clause (“such markings…can be a gold mine to scholars”) to create a compound sentence. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two independent clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between two independent clauses. Choice D is incorrect because a comma is needed to mark the boundary between two coordinated independent clauses.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "5f56ee2e","Question": "Objects ranging from the Kikkoman soy sauce bottle to the Yamaha VMAX motorcycle to the Komachi bullet train ______ designed by twentieth-century industrial designer Kenji Ekuan. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "was","B": "is","C": "has been","D": "were","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The plural verb 'were' agrees in number with the plural subject 'objects.' Choice A is incorrect because the singular verb 'was' doesn’t agree in number with the plural subject 'objects.' Choice B is incorrect because the singular verb 'is' doesn’t agree in number with the plural subject 'objects.' Choice C is incorrect because the singular verb 'has been' doesn’t agree in number with the plural subject 'objects.'","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "5ff54894","Question": "In 2018, the innovative works of Congolese sculptor and architect Bodys Isek ______ were featured in City Dreams, a solo exhibition at New York’s Museum of Modern Art. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Kingelez;","B": "Kingelez,","C": "Kingelez","D": "Kingelez:","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a subject and a verb. No punctuation is needed when the subject of a sentence is immediately followed by a main verb. In this case, the sentence’s subject (“the innovative works of Congolese sculptor and architect Bodys Isek Kingelez”) is followed by the main verb “were featured,” and no punctuation should come between them. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "60e5fc31","Question": "A pioneer in the ﬁeld of taphonomy (the study of how organic remains become fossils), ______ may be just as prevalent in the fossil record as those of thick-shelled organisms. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "fossils of thin-shelled organisms, na Behrensmeyer demonstrated in a 2005 analysis,","B": "Anna hrensmeyer demonstrated in a 2005 analysis that fossils of thin-shelled organisms","C": "it was demonstrated in a 2005 analysis by Anna Behrensmeyer that fossils of thin-shelled organisms","D": "a 2005 analysis—by Anna Behrensmeyer—demonstrated that fossils of thin-shelled organisms","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice makes the noun phrase “Anna Behrensmeyer” the subject of the sentence and places it immediately after the modifying phrase “a pioneer…fossils.” In doing so, this choice clearly establishes that Anna Behrensmeyer—and not another noun in the sentence—is a pioneer in the ﬁeld of taphonomy. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “fossils of thin-shelled organisms” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the “fossils” are a pioneer in the ﬁeld of taphonomy. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the pronoun “it” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that “it” is a pioneer in the ﬁeld of taphonomy. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “a 2005 analysis” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that “a 2005 analysis” is a pioneer in the ﬁeld of taphonomy.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "62200e28","Question": "Dr. Rocío Paola Caballero-Gill is a paleoceanographer. This means that Dr. Caballero-Gill doesn’t just study oceans as they are today. She uses chemistry and fossil evidence ______ oceans as they were in the past. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "has studied","B": "to study","C": "studied","D": "studies","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verb forms within a sentence. The nonﬁnite to- inﬁnitive verb “to study” is correctly used to form a subordinate clause that indicates what Dr. Caballero-Gill uses chemistry and fossil evidence for (to study oceans as they were in the past). Choice A is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The ﬁnite verb “has studied” can’t be used in this way to form a subordinate clause that indicates what Dr. Caballero-Gill uses the evidence for. Choice C is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The ﬁnite verb “studied” can’t be used in this way to form a subordinate clause that indicates what Dr. Caballero-Gill uses the evidence for. Choice D is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The ﬁnite verb “studies” can’t be used in this way to form a subordinate clause that indicates what Dr. Caballero- Gill uses the evidence for.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "62c20dbb","Question": "The Tantaquidgeon Museum in Uncasville, Connecticut, was founded in 1931 with the goal of showcasing the culture and history of the Mohegan ______ today, nearly a century later, it is the oldest Native-owned and -operated museum in the country. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Tribe, and","B": "Tribe","C": "Tribe and","D": "Tribe,","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. This choice uses a comma and a coordinating conjunction (“and”) to join two independent clauses (“The Tantaquidgeon…Tribe” and “Today…country”). Choice B is incorrect. This choice results in a grammar error known as a run-on sentence. The clauses before and after “Tribe” are both independent, so they need to be separated with some sort of punctuation. Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a grammar error known as a run-on sentence. The clauses before and after “and” are both independent, so they can’t be linked with just a conjunction. A comma would also be required. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a grammar error called a comma splice. The clauses before and after “Tribe” are both independent, so they can’t be linked with just a comma. A coordinating conjunction like “and” or “but” would also be required.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "67e5ebde","Question": "Researcher Lin Zhi developed a process for increasing the tensile strength—measured in gigapascals, or GPa—of silkworm ______ dissolving and reweaving the silk in a solution of iron metal ions, zinc, and sugar, Zhi increased the amount of force required to stretch it from approximately 0.5 GPa to 2 GPa. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "silk, by","B": "silk by","C": "silk and by","D": "silk. By","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The independent clauses 'researcher Lin Zhi…silk' and 'by dissolving…2 GPa' can be grammatically separated by a period. They can stand alone as sentences, and this is the only choice that lets them do that. Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a grammar error called a comma splice. 'Researcher Lin Zhi…silk' and 'by dissolving…2 GPa' are both independent clauses. They need to either be separated with punctuation like a period or a semicolon, or they need to be connected by a comma and a coordinating conjunction like 'and.' A comma alone isn’t enough. Choice B is incorrect. This choice results in a grammar error called a run-on sentence. 'Researcher Lin Zhi…silk' and 'by dissolving…2 GPa' are both independent clauses. They need to either be separated with punctuation like a period or a semicolon, or they need to be connected by a comma and a coordinating conjunction like 'and.' Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a grammar error called a run-on sentence. 'Researcher Lin Zhi…silk' and 'by dissolving…2 GPa' are both independent clauses. The coordinating conjunction 'and' isn’t enough to link them by itself. We need a comma, too.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "67f2e137","Question": "The sun never sets during the Arctic summer in the Far North. In response, reindeer in this region must change their sleep habits. Instead of resting when it gets dark, they rest when they need ______ their food. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "digest","B": "will digest","C": "to digest","D": "digesting","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. Working together with the ﬁnite verb 'need,' the nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive verb 'to digest' is correctly used to form a subordinate clause that describes what the reindeer need. Choice A is incorrect because the verb 'digest' (in either its ﬁnite or nonﬁnite form) can’t be used in this way with the ﬁnite verb 'need.' Choice B is incorrect because the ﬁnite verb 'will digest' can’t be used in this way with the ﬁnite verb 'need.' Choice D is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle 'digesting' can’t be used in this way with the ﬁnite verb 'need.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "6b030cfe","Question": "In the late 1960s, inspired in part by the sight of laundry hanging on a clothesline, African American abstract painter Sam Gilliam began to create his iconic “Drape” paintings. He applied bold, saturated hues to large canvases and ______ them from ceilings or walls, causing the drooping fabric to cascade in dramatic loops and curves. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "to have suspended","B": "suspending","C": "to suspend","D": "suspended","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The past tense of 'suspended' matches the past tense of 'applied,' which has the same subject ('he') and takes place in the same context: 'He applied…and [he] suspended.' Choice A is incorrect. The perfect inﬁnitive 'to have suspended' doesn’t match the past tense of 'applied,' and it can’t serve as a verb on its own. These are both verbs with the same subject and in the same context, so there’s no need to shift tenses. Choice B is incorrect. The present participle 'suspending' doesn’t match the past tense of 'applied,' and it can’t serve as a verb on its own. These are both verbs with the same subject and in the same context, so there’s no need to shift tenses. Choice C is incorrect. The inﬁnitive 'to suspend' doesn’t match the past tense of 'applied,' and it can’t serve as a verb on its own. These are both verbs with the same subject and in the same context, so there’s no need to shift tenses.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "6ccba054","Question": "The African Games Co-production Market, one of over 180 annual international conferences supporting video game development, ______ the growth of the African gaming industry by helping start-up studios in Africa ﬁnd partners. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "promote","B": "are promoting","C": "promotes","D": "have promoted","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The subject of the sentence is “The African Games Co-production Market.” That’s one market, so it’s a singular noun, which means it needs a singular verb. “Promotes” is the only singular verb among the choices. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a subject-verb agreement error. The subject “The African Games Co-production Market” is singular, but the verb “promote” is plural. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a subject-verb agreement error. The subject “The African Games Co-production Market” is singular, but the verb “are promoting” is plural. Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a subject-verb agreement error. The subject “The African Games Co-production Market” is singular, but the verb “have promoted” is plural.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "6e5f637a","Question": "In addition to advocating for South America’s independence in two political treatises, the Cartagena Manifesto and the Letter from Jamaica, Simón Bolívar personally led armies against the Spanish, liberating three South American territories—New Granada (present-day Colombia and Panama), Venezuela, and Quito (present-day ______ from colonial rule. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Ecuador,)","B": "Ecuador)","C": "Ecuador),","D": "Ecuador)—","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary element within a sentence. The dash after “Ecuador” and the closing parenthesis pairs with the dash after “territories” to separate the supplementary element (“New…Ecuador”) from the rest of the sentence. The supplementary element speciﬁes the three South American territories that Simón Bolívar liberated, and the pair of dashes indicates that this element could be removed without affecting the grammatical coherence of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Furthermore, punctuation isn’t needed between “Ecuador” and the closing parenthesis. Choice B is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice C is incorrect because a comma can’t be paired with a dash to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "6f4a9e8c","Question": "In her book The Woman Warrior: Memoirs of a Girlhood Among Ghosts, author Maxine Hong Kingston examines themes ______ childhood, womanhood, and Chinese American identity by intertwining autobiography and mythology. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "of:","B": "of","C": "of—","D": "of,","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. “Themes of childhood” is one noun phrase, with “themes of” implicitly carrying over to the other items on the list (“themes of childhood, [themes of] womanhood, and [themes of] Chinese American identity”). Choice A is incorrect. This choice inappropriately breaks up the introduction of a list. Also, “In her book…themes of” is not an independent clause, thanks to the dangling “of” at the end, so it can’t precede a colon. Choice C is incorrect. This choice inappropriately breaks up the introduction of a list. Also, “In her book…themes of” is not an independent clause, thanks to the dangling “of” at the end, so it can’t precede a single dash. Choice D is incorrect. This choice inappropriately breaks up the introduction of a list. “Themes of” implicitly carries over to each item on the list (“themes of childhood, [themes of] womanhood, and [themes of] Chinese American identity”), so we don’t want to use a comma to separate it.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "6f4d8396","Question": "Beatrix Potter is perhaps best known for writing and illustrating children’s books such as The Tale of Peter Rabbit (1902), but she also dedicated herself to mycology, the study of ______ more than 350 paintings of the fungal species she observed in nature and submitting her research on spore germination to the Linnean Society of London. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "fungi; producing","B": "fungi. Producing","C": "fungi producing","D": "fungi, producing","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between two supplementary phrases following the coordinate clause (“but she…mycology”). This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the supplementary noun phrase (“the study of fungi”) that deﬁnes the term “mycology” and the supplementary participial phrase (“producing...London”) that provides additional information about the extent to which Potter dedicated herself to mycology. Choice A is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join two supplementary phrases following a coordinate clause. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with “producing.” Choice C is incorrect. The lack of punctuation results in a sentence that illogically suggests that the study of fungi is producing more than 350 paintings.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "7238af74","Question": "In 2000, Nora de Hoyos Comstock, herself an owner of a successful consulting ﬁrm, sought to increase Latina representation in corporate ______ founded Las Comadres para las Americas, an international community that for over two decades has served as a resource and information network for Latina business professionals. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "settings she","B": "settings, she","C": "settings and she","D": "settings. She","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. It appropriately uses a period to mark the end of one independent clause ('In 2000…settings') and the start of another ('She founded…professionals'). Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence error. Both the clause before the blank ('In 2000…settings') and the clause after the blank ('she…professionals') are independent clauses, so they need to be separated by punctuation. Choice B is incorrect. This choice results in a comma splice error. It incorrectly joins two independent clauses with just a comma. Linking two independent clauses with a comma also requires the use of a coordinating conjunction (like for, and, nor, but, or, yet, or so). Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence, an error caused when two independent clauses are joined without punctuation or appropriate conjunctions. Since both the clause before the blank ('In 2000… settings') and the clause after the blank ('she…professionals') are independent, a comma would be required in addition to the coordinating conjunction 'and.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},
{"ID": "7257566a","Question": "In 2008, two years after the death of science ﬁction writer Octavia Butler, the Huntington Library in ______ received a collection of more than 8,000 items, including Butler’s private notes, research materials, manuscripts, photos, and drawings. Today, the Octavia E. Butler Collection is one of the most researched archives at the library. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "California,","B": "California:","C": "lifornia—","D": "California","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. No punctuation should separate the subject of the sentence (“the Huntington Library in California”) from its verb (“received”). Choice A is incorrect. No punctuation should separate the subject of the sentence (“the Huntington Library in California”) from its verb (“received”). Choice B is incorrect. No punctuation should separate the subject of the sentence (“the Huntington Library in California”) from its verb (“received”). Choice C is incorrect. No punctuation should separate the subject of the sentence (“the Huntington Library in California”) from its verb (“received”).","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "72770fa9","Question": "Sociologist Alton Okinaka sits on the review board tasked with adding new sites to the Hawai‘i Register of Historic Places, which includes Pi‘ilanihale Heiau and the ‘Ōpaeka‘a Road Bridge. Okinaka doesn’t make such decisions ______ all historical designations must be approved by a group of nine other experts from the ﬁelds of architecture, archaeology, history, and Hawaiian culture. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "single-handedly, however;","B": "single-handedly; however,","C": "single-handedly, however,","D": "single-handedly however","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary word or phrase between two main clauses. This choice correctly uses a comma to separate the supplementary adverb “however” from the preceding main clause (“Okinaka doesn’t…single-handedly”) and a semicolon to join the next main clause (“all…culture”) to the rest of the sentence. Further, placing the semicolon after “however” correctly indicates that the information in the preceding main clause (Okinaka doesn’t make such decisions single-handedly) is contrary to what might be assumed from the information in the previous sentence (Okinaka sits on the review board that adds new sites to the Hawaii Register of Historic Places). Choice B is incorrect because placing the semicolon after “single-handedly” and the comma after “however” illogically indicates that the information in the next main clause (all historical designations must be approved by a group of experts) is contrary to the information in the previous clause (Okinaka doesn’t make such decisions single-handedly). Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Commas can’t be used in this way to punctuate a supplementary word or phrase between two main clauses. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "7421ada8","Question": "After a spate of illnesses as a child, Wilma Rudolph was told she might never walk again. Defying all odds, Rudolph didn’t just walk, she ______ the 1960 Summer Olympics in Rome, she won both the 100- and 200-meter dashes and clinched ﬁrst place for her team in the 4x100-meter relay, becoming the ﬁrst US woman to win three gold medals in a single Olympics. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "ran—fast—during","B": "ran—fast during","C": "ran—fast, during","D": "ran—fast. ring","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence (“Defying…fast”) and another sentence that begins with a supplementary phrase (“During…Olympics”). Choice A is incorrect. When a dash is present in a sentence (“ran—fast”), it’s not conventional to use another dash (“fast— during”) to mark the boundary between sentences because it creates a potentially confusing sentence. In this context, a period, semicolon, or colon would be clear and more conventional. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences (“Defying…fast”) and (“during…Olympics”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "764b7545","Question": "British scientists James Watson and Francis Crick won the Nobel Prize in part for their 1953 paper announcing the double helix structure of DNA, but it is misleading to say that Watson and Crick discovered the double helix. ______ ﬁndings were based on a famous X-ray image of DNA ﬁbers, “Photo 51,” developed by X-ray crystallographer Rosalind Franklin and her graduate student Raymond Gosling. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "They’re","B": "It’s","C": "Their","D": "Its","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of possessive determiners. The plural possessive determiner “their” agrees in number with the plural conjoined noun phrase “Watson and Crick” and thus indicates that the ﬁndings were those of Watson and Crick. Choice A is incorrect because “they’re” is the contraction for “they are,” not a possessive determiner. Choice B is incorrect because “it’s” is the contraction for “it is” or “it has,” not a possessive determiner. Choice D is incorrect because the singular possessive determiner “its” doesn’t agree in number with the plural conjoined noun phrase “Watson and Crick.”","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "76755c9a","Question": "Former First Lady of the United States Eleanor Roosevelt and Indian activist and educator Hansa Mehta were instrumental in drafting the United Nations’ Universal Declaration of Human Rights, a document that ______ the basic freedoms to which all people are entitled. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "have outlined","B": "were outlining","C": "outlines","D": "outline","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb “outlines” agrees in number with the singular subject “document.” Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb “have outlined” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “document.” Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb “were outlining” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “document.” Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb “outline” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “document.”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "76d0d8f1","Question": "In the 2011 documentary The Barber of Birmingham, civil rights activist James Armstrong recounts how his barbershop in Birmingham, Alabama, ______ as a political hub for members of the Black community during the 1950s. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "serving","B": "having served","C": "served","D": "to serve","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verb forms within a sentence. Relative clauses, such as the one beginning with 'how,' require a ﬁnite (tensed) verb, a verb that can function as the main verb of a clause. This choice correctly supplies the clause with the ﬁnite past tense verb 'served.' Choice A is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The nonﬁnite participle 'serving' doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice B is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The nonﬁnite participle 'having served' doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice D is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive 'to serve' doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "776c0a46","Question": "The haiku-like poems of Tomas Tranströmer, which present nature- and dream-inﬂuenced images in crisp, spare language, have earned the Swedish poet praise from leading contemporary ______ them Nigerian American essayist and novelist Teju Cole, who has written that Tranströmer’s works “contain a luminous simplicity.” Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "writers. ong","B": "writers among","C": "writers; among","D": "writers, among","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between a main clause and a supplementary phrase. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the main clause (“The haiku-like…writers”) and the supplementary phrase (“among…Cole”) that speciﬁes a contemporary writer who has praised Tomas Tranströmer’s haiku-like poems. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with “among.” Choice B is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the main clause and the supplementary phrase with appropriate punctuation. Choice C is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join the main clause (“The haiku-like… writers”) and the supplementary phrase (“among…Cole”).","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "77af0ba3","Question": "In his groundbreaking book Bengali Harlem and the Lost Histories of South Asian America, Vivek Bald uses newspaper articles, census records, ships’ logs, and memoirs to tell the ______ who made New York City their home in the early twentieth century. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "story’s of the South ian immigrants","B": "story’s of the South Asian immigrants’","C": "stories of the South Asian immigrants","D": "stories’ of the South Asian immigrant’s","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of plural and possessive nouns. The plural nouns “stories” and “immigrants” correctly indicate that the memoir tells multiple stories of multiple immigrants. Choice A is incorrect because the context requires the plural noun “stories,” not the singular possessive noun “story’s.” Choice B is incorrect because the context requires the plural nouns “stories” and “immigrants,” not the singular possessive noun “story’s” and the plural possessive noun “immigrants’.” Choice D is incorrect because the context requires the plural nouns “stories” and “immigrants,” not the plural possessive noun “stories’” and the singular possessive noun “immigrant’s.”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "78fdad9b","Question": "Materials scientist Marie-Agathe Charpagne and her colleagues believed they could improve on the multicomponent alloy NiCoCr, an equal-proportions mixture of nickel (Ni), cobalt (Co), and chromium (Cr), by replacing chromium with ruthenium ______ the alloy that resulted, NiCoRu, turned out to be an unsuitable replacement for NiCoCr. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "(Ru)","B": "(Ru) but","C": "(Ru),","D": "(Ru), but","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses. This choice correctly uses a comma and the coordinating conjunction “but” to join the ﬁrst main clause (“Materials…Ru”) and the second main clause (“the alloy…NiCoCr”). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice B is incorrect because when coordinating two longer main clauses such as these, it’s conventional to use a comma before the coordinating conjunction. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "79920251","Question": "With its towering, six-spired exterior of granitelike quartz monzonite, the Salt Lake Temple is one of the most instantly recognizable structures in the state of Utah. However, many people do not know that ______ built over the course of forty years, with construction beginning in 1853 and ending in 1893. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "it was","B": "one was","C": "they were","D": "both were","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is pronoun-antecedent agreement. The singular pronoun 'it' agrees in number with the singular antecedent 'the Salt Lake Temple.' Choice B is incorrect because the singular pronoun 'one' is ambiguous in this context; the resulting sentence leaves unclear whether there is only one Salt Lake temple or multiple. Choice C is incorrect because the plural pronoun 'they' doesn’t agree in number with the singular antecedent 'the Salt Lake Temple.' Choice D is incorrect because the plural pronoun 'both' doesn’t agree in number with the singular antecedent 'the Salt Lake Temple.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "79f6b5f6","Question": "In the early twentieth century, Joseph Kekuku and other Hawaiian ______ in the mainland United States to the bright and lilting sound of the kīkā kila, or Hawaiian steel guitar. The instrument soon became a ﬁxture in American blues and country music. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "musicians introduced audiences","B": "musicians’ introduced audiences’","C": "musician’s introduced audience’s","D": "musicians’ introduced audiences","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of plural nouns. The plural nouns 'musicians' and 'audiences' correctly indicate that there were multiple musicians introducing the music to multiple audiences. Choice B is incorrect because the context requires the plural nouns 'musicians' and 'audiences,' not the plural possessive nouns 'musicians’' and 'audiences’.' Choice C is incorrect because the context requires the plural nouns 'musicians' and 'audiences,' not the singular possessive nouns 'musician’s' and 'audience’s.' Choice D is incorrect because the context requires the plural noun 'musicians,' not the plural possessive noun 'musicians’.'","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "7a7070f7","Question": "A subseasonal weather forecast attempts to predict weather conditions three to four weeks in ______ its predictions are therefore more short-term than those of the seasonal forecast, which attempts to predict the weather more than a month in advance. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "advance,","B": "advance","C": "advance;","D": "advance and","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The clause “A subseasonal…advance” and the clause “its predictions…forecast” are both independent clauses, so using a semicolon to separate them is grammatically correct. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a run-on sentence error. The clause “A subseasonal…advance” and the clause “its predictions…forecast” are both independent clauses, so a comma is not enough to separate them. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a run-on sentence error. The clause “A subseasonal…advance” and the clause “its predictions…forecast” are both independent clauses, so they need to be separated with speciﬁc punctuation (a period, a semi-colon, a colon, a dash, or a comma + a coordinating conjunction). Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a run-on sentence error. The clause “A subseasonal…advance” and the clause “its predictions…forecast” are both independent clauses, so the word “and” by itself is not enough to separate them. There would need to be a comma before “and” for this choice to work.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "7bddd829","Question": "The poem Beowulf begins with the word “hwæt,” which is an Old English ______ as “hark!” or “listen!” in some versions, the word was playfully rendered as “bro!” by Maria Dahvana Headley in her 2020 translation of the poem. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "exclamation, translated","B": "exclamation and translated","C": "exclamation translated","D": "exclamation. Translated","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence ('The poem…exclamation') and another sentence that begins with a supplementary element ('Translated…poem'). The supplementary element 'translated as ‘hark!’ or ‘listen!’ in some versions' modiﬁes the subject of the second sentence, 'the word' (referring to hwæt). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a comma splice after 'exclamation.' A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice B is incorrect. Without a comma preceding it, the conjunction 'and' can’t be used in this way to join sentences. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice after 'versions.' A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "7df1890b","Question": "The ﬁrst computerized spreadsheet, Dan Bricklin’s VisiCalc, improved ﬁnancial recordkeeping not only by providing users with an easy means of adjusting data in spreadsheets but also by automatically updating all calculations that were dependent on these ______ to VisiCalc’s release, changing a paper spreadsheet often required redoing the entire sheet by hand, a process that could take days. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "adjustments prior","B": "adjustments, prior","C": "adjustments. Prior","D": "adjustments and prior","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period is used correctly to mark the boundary between the ﬁrst sentence (“The...adjustments”) and the second sentence (“Prior...days”). Because the adverbial phrase beginning with “prior” indicates when changing a spreadsheet required redoing the sheet by hand, that phrase belongs with the second sentence. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. Two sentences are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice D is incorrect. Without a comma preceding it, the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to join the sentences.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "7ecd64c8","Question": "During the American Civil War, Thomas Morris Chester braved the front lines as a war correspondent for the Philadelphia Press. Amplifying the voices and experiences of Black soldiers ______ of particular importance to Chester, who later became an activist and lawyer during the postwar Reconstruction period. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "were","B": "have been","C": "are","D": "was","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb 'was' agrees in number with the singular subject 'amplifying.' Gerunds such as 'amplifying' are always singular. Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb 'were' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'amplifying.' Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb 'have been' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'amplifying.' Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb 'are' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'amplifying.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "7fe1b853","Question": "A member of the Cherokee Nation, Mary Golda Ross is renowned for her contributions to NASA’s Planetary Flight Handbook, which ______ detailed mathematical guidance for missions to Mars and Venus. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "provided","B": "having provided","C": "to provide","D": "providing","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of ﬁnite verbs in a relative clause. Relative clauses, such as the one beginning with “which,” require a ﬁnite verb, a verb that can function as the main verb of a clause. This choice correctly supplies the clause with the ﬁnite past tense verb “provided.” Choice B is incorrect because the non-ﬁnite participle “having provided” doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice C is incorrect because the non-ﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to provide” doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice D is incorrect because the non-ﬁnite participle “providing” doesn’t supply the clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "815b1a10","Question": "Researchers studying magnetosensation have determined why some soil-dwelling roundworms in the Southern Hemisphere move in the opposite direction of Earth’s magnetic ﬁeld when searching for ______ in the Northern Hemisphere, the magnetic ﬁeld points down, into the ground, but in the Southern Hemisphere, it points up, toward the surface and away from worms’ food sources. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "food:","B": "food,","C": "food while","D": "food","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is colon use within a sentence. A colon used in this way introduces information that illustrates or explains information that has come before it. In this case, the colon introduces the following explanation of why some roundworms in the Southern Hemisphere move in the opposite direction of Earth’s magnetic ﬁeld. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to join two long independent clauses (“Researchers…food” and “in…sources”) such as these. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two clauses (“Researchers…food” and “in…sources”) are fused without punctuation. Furthermore, the conjunction “while” fails to indicate that what follows is an explanation of why some roundworms in the Southern Hemisphere move in the opposite direction of Earth’s magnetic ﬁeld. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two clauses (“Researchers…food” and “in…sources”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "81a45931","Question": "In 1955, Indian Bengali ﬁlmmaker Satyajit Ray released his ﬁrst movie, Pather ______ quiet black-and-white drama about a family in rural India, Ray’s ﬁlm was quite different from the loud, colorful action-romance movies that were popular at the time. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Panchali a","B": "Panchali, which was a","C": "Panchali, a","D": "Panchali. A","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence ('In…Panchali') and another ('A quiet…time'). The phrase beginning with 'a quiet' modiﬁes the subject of the next sentence, 'Ray’s ﬁlm.' Choice A is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "82a6a62a","Question": "Because a cycle of lunar phases ______ 29.5 days to complete, it’s possible to observe two full moons in a single month, one at the beginning and one at the end. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "are taking","B": "have taken","C": "take","D": "takes","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb 'takes' agrees in number with the singular subject 'a cycle of lunar phases.' Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb 'are taking' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'a cycle of lunar phases.' Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb 'have taken' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'a cycle of lunar phases.' Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb 'take' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'a cycle of lunar phases.'","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "83c646a9","Question": "Using satellite remote sensing, Dr. Catherine Nakalembe, director of NASA’s Harvest Africa initiative, gathers important data on crop health. Nakalembe doesn’t just compile the ______ she also shares her ﬁndings with African farmers, enabling them to make data-driven decisions about managing critical food crops. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "information, though;","B": "information, though,","C": "information; though","D": "information though,","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. This choice uses a semicolon to join two independent clauses ('Nakalembe doesn’t just… though' and 'she also shares...'). This choice also appropriately includes 'though' in the ﬁrst clause, where it logically belongs. Choice B is incorrect. This choice results in a grammar error called a comma splice. It incorrectly joins two independent clauses with only a comma instead of a comma and a coordinating conjunction like 'and' or 'but.' 'Though' is a transition word, but it’s not a coordinating conjunction. Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error. A semicolon can only be used to link two independent clauses. However, if 'though' is included in the second clause, it turns the second clause into a dependent clause, so a semicolon can’t be used after 'information.' Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a grammar error called a comma splice. It incorrectly joins two independent clauses with only a comma instead of a comma and a coordinating conjunction like 'and' or 'but.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "842891bb","Question": "In her analysis of Edith Wharton’s The House of Mirth (1905), scholar Candace Waid observes that the novel depicts the upper classes of New York society as “consumed by the appetite of a soulless ______ an apt assessment given that The House of Mirth is set during the Gilded Age, a period marked by rapid industrialization, economic greed, and widening wealth disparities. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "materialism”; and","B": "materialism” and","C": "materialism,”","D": "materialism”","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a main clause and a supplementary noun phrase. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the main clause (“scholar…materialism”) and the supplementary noun phrase (“an apt assessment”) that describes Waid’s observation about how The House of Mirth depicts the upper classes of New York society. Choice A is incorrect because a semicolon and the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between a main clause and a supplementary noun phrase. Choice B is incorrect. Joining the main clause (“scholar… materialism”) and the following noun phrase with the conjunction “and” results in a confusing and illogical sentence that suggests that the novel depicts the upper classes of New York society as “an apt assessment,” which doesn’t make sense in this context. Choice D is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the main clause and the supplementary noun phrase with appropriate punctuation.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "85cac465","Question": "While exploring Nevada’s Gypsum Cave in 1930, Seneca and Abenaki archaeologist Bertha Parker made her most famous discovery: the skull of a now-extinct ground sloth (Nothrotheriops shastensis) alongside human-made tools. Parker’s crucial ﬁnding was the ﬁrst ______ humans in North America as far back as 10,000 years ago. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "places","B": "placed","C": "place","D": "to place","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The object for the verb 'was' is 'ﬁrst,' and 'to place' is acting as a modiﬁer for 'ﬁrst.' What was the ﬁnding? It was 'the ﬁrst.' The ﬁrst to do what? The ﬁrst 'to place humans in North America' 10,000 years ago. When a verb serves as a modiﬁer within a noun phrase, it must be nonﬁnite (i.e., not conjugated to a speciﬁc subject). The inﬁnitive form 'to place' is the only nonﬁnite option among the choices that makes sense in context. Choice A is incorrect. The object for the verb 'was' is 'ﬁrst,' and 'places' is acting as a modiﬁer for 'ﬁrst.' What was the thing that Parker’s ﬁnding did? What was it the ﬁrst to do? Place humans in North America 10,000 years ago. When a verb acts as a modiﬁer, it must be nonﬁnite (i.e., not conjugated to a speciﬁc subject), but 'places' is a ﬁnite form of the verb. Choice B is incorrect. The object for the verb 'was' is 'ﬁrst,' and 'placed' is acting to modify 'ﬁrst.' What was it that Parker’s ﬁnding was the ﬁrst to do? Place humans in North America 10,000 years ago. When a verb acts as a modiﬁer, it must be nonﬁnite (i.e., not conjugated to a speciﬁc subject), but 'placed' is a ﬁnite form. 'Placed' can also be a past participle, but that wouldn’t make sense here because the meaning of 'the ﬁrst placed humans' would be unclear. Choice C is incorrect. The object for the verb 'was' is 'ﬁrst,' and 'place' is modifying 'ﬁrst.' What was the thing that Parker’s ﬁnding did? What was it the ﬁrst to do? Place humans in North America. When a verb acts as a modiﬁer, it must be nonﬁnite (i.e., not conjugated to a speciﬁc subject), but 'place' is a ﬁnite form of the verb. Additionally, 'place' can’t serve as a noun here, because it results in an illogical sentence (the 'ﬁnding' wasn’t 'the ﬁrst place').","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "85f8e218","Question": "Bengali author Toru Dutt’s A Sheaf Gleaned in French Fields (1876), a volume of English translations of French poems, ______ scholars’ understanding of the transnational and multilingual contexts in which Dutt lived and worked. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "has enhanced","B": "are enhancing","C": "have enhanced","D": "enhance","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb “has enhanced” agrees in number with the singular subject “A Sheaf Gleaned in French Fields,” which is the title of a book of poems. Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb “are enhancing” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “A Sheaf Gleaned in French Fields.” Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb “have enhanced” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “A Sheaf Gleaned in French Fields.” Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb “enhance” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “A Sheaf Gleaned in French Fields.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "88781897","Question": "Oglala Lakota poet Layli Long Soldier’s star quilt poems offer an unusually open-ended reading experience. With ______ eight panels of text stitched together in the shape of a traditional eight-pointed Lakota star quilt, the poems present viewers with a seemingly inﬁnite number of ways to read them. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "their","B": "it’s","C": "they’re","D": "its","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of possessive determiners. The plural possessive determiner 'their' agrees in number with the plural noun 'the poems,' thus indicating that the poems had eight panels of text stitched together in the shape of a traditional eight-pointed Lakota star quilt. Choice B is incorrect because 'it’s' is the contraction for 'it is' or 'it has,' not a possessive determiner. Choice C is incorrect because 'they’re' is the contraction for 'they are,' not a possessive determiner. Choice D is incorrect because the singular possessive determiner 'its' doesn’t agree in number with the plural noun 'the poems.'","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "8b86da1c","Question": "Planetary scientist Briony Horgan and her colleagues have determined that as much as 25 percent of the sand on Mars is composed of impact spherules. These spherical bits of glass form when asteroids collide with the planet, ejecting bits of molten rock into the atmosphere that, after cooling and solidifying into glass, ______ back onto Mars’s surface. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "to rain","B": "raining","C": "having rained","D": "rain","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. 'That…[rain] back onto Mars’s surface' is a relative clause that describes the 'bits of molten rock.' Forming the clause requires a conjugated, ﬁnite verb, and this is the only choice that provides that. Choice A is incorrect. 'To rain' is an inﬁnitive and can’t serve as the main verb of a clause. A conjugated verb is needed here to form the main verb of the relative clause 'that…[rain] back onto Mars’s surface,' which describes the 'bits of molten rock.' Choice B is incorrect. 'Raining' is a present participle and, on its own, can’t serve as the main verb of a clause. A conjugated verb is needed here to form the main verb of the relative clause 'that…[rain] back onto Mars’s surface,' which describes the 'bits of molten rock.' Choice C is incorrect. 'Having rained' is a perfect participle and can’t serve as the main verb of a clause. A conjugated verb is needed here to form the main verb of the relative clause 'that…[rain] back onto Mars’s surface,' which describes the 'bits of molten rock.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "8c2c0671","Question": "Winding through the ice atop Norway’s Jotunheim Mountains is the Lendbreen pass, an ancient route that was used by hunters, farmers, traders, and travelers in the Middle Ages before eventually falling into disuse. Recently, archeologists have ______ knives, horseshoes, wool tunics, and thousands of other artifacts from the icy pass. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "unearthed:","B": "unearthed,","C": "unearthed—","D": "unearthed","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. No punctuation should separate the verb 'unearthed' and its objects (i.e, what was 'unearthed'): 'knives, horseshoes, wool tunics, and thousands of other artifacts.' Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error, separating the verb 'unearthed' from its objects (i.e, what was 'unearthed') with a colon. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error, separating the verb 'unearthed' from its objects (i.e, what was 'unearthed') with a comma. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error, separating the verb 'unearthed' from its objects (i.e, what was 'unearthed') with a dash.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "8de5071a","Question": "In 2017, artists Isabel and Ruben Toledo redesigned the costumes and sets for The Miami City Ballet’s production of The ______ to reviewers, the Toledos’ designs helped infuse the production with elements of Miami’s Latin American culture. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Nutcracker according,","B": "Nutcracker, according","C": "Nutcracker according","D": "Nutcracker. According","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence (“In 2017...Nutcracker”) and another (“According...culture”). The supplementary element “according to reviewers” modiﬁes the main clause of the second sentence (“the Toledos’...culture”). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Furthermore, no punctuation is needed within the supplementary element “according to reviewers.” Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "911b32da","Question": "A conceptual artist and designer embraced by both the art world and the fashion ______ Mary Ping was chosen to curate the exhibition Front Row: Chinese American Designers for the Museum of Chinese in America. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "world","B": "world:","C": "world;","D": "world,","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a supplementary phrase and a main clause. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the supplementary phrase (“A conceptual artist… world”), which describes Mary Ping, and the main clause (“Mary…America”). Choice A is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the supplementary phrase (“A conceptual artist…world”) and the main clause (“Mary…America”) with appropriate punctuation. Choice B is incorrect because a colon can’t be used in this way to join the supplementary phrase (“A conceptual artist…world”) and the main clause (“Mary…America”). In this context, the colon incorrectly suggests that the information in the supplementary phrase is an explanation or ampliﬁcation of the information in the main clause (Mary Ping being chosen to curate the exhibition), which isn’t the case. Choice C is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join the supplementary phrase (“A conceptual artist…world”) and the main clause (“Mary…America”). Semicolons are conventionally used to separate two main clauses or to separate items in a complex series.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "931ec749","Question": "Slam poet Elizabeth Acevedo’s debut novel The Poet X, winner of the 2018 National Book Award for Young People’s Literature, is composed of ______ protagonist, ﬁfteen-year-old Xiomara Batista. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "poems putatively written by the novel’s","B": "poem’s putatively written by the novel’s","C": "poem’s putatively written by the novels’","D": "poems putatively written by the novels’","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. Nothing belongs to the “poems” in the sentence, so it should not be possessive—just a simple plural noun. The protagonist does belong to the novel—it’s the protagonist of the novel—so “novel” needs to be a singular possessive noun. Choice B is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. This choice uses the singular possessive “poem’s,” but the text indicates that it should be the simple plural “poems”: there is more than one poem, and nothing belongs to the poems. Choice C is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. This choice uses the singular possessive “poem’s,” but the text indicates that it should be the simple plural “poems”: there is more than one poem, and nothing belongs to the poems. This choice also uses the plural possessive “novels’,” which is incorrect because there is only one novel. Choice D is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. This choice uses the plural possessive “novels’,” which is incorrect because there is only one novel, so it should be the singular possessive “novel’s.” .","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "93590689","Question": "In paleontology, the term “Elvis taxon” gets applied to a newly identiﬁed living species that was once presumed to be extinct. Like an Elvis impersonator who might bear a striking resemblance to the late musical icon Elvis Presley himself, an Elvis taxon is not the real thing, ______ is a misidentiﬁed look-alike. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "however but it","B": "however it","C": "however, it","D": "however. It","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The clause “Like an Elvis impersonator…real thing” and the clause “it is…look-alike” are both independent clauses, so making them into two separate sentences is grammatically correct. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a run-on sentence error. The clause “Like an Elvis impersonator…real thing” and the clause “it is…look-alike” are both independent clauses, so they need to be separated with at least a comma + a coordinating conjunction. This choice provides the coordinating conjunction “but,” but it’s missing a comma. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a run-on sentence error. The clause “Like an Elvis impersonator…real thing” and the clause “it is…look-alike” are both independent clauses, so they need to be separated with a semicolon, a colon, a dash, a period, or a comma + a coordinating conjunction. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a run-on sentence error. The clause “Like an Elvis impersonator…real thing” and the clause “it is…look-alike” are both independent clauses, so they need to be separated with at least a comma + a coordinating conjunction. This choice provides a comma, but it’s missing a coordinating conjunction.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "93fe1196","Question": "Led by Syrian American astronomer Shadia Habbal, the Solar Wind Sherpas are an intrepid team of scientists who travel the globe to study solar winds, the streams of particles emanating from the Sun that are only visible from certain locations during a total solar eclipse. When such an eclipse is imminent, the Sherpas pack up their telescopes and ______ ready. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "get","B": "had gotten","C": "got","D": "were getting","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense in a sentence. In this choice, the present tense verb “get” is consistent with the other present tense verbs (“are,” “travel,” and “pack”) used to describe the Sherpas and their activities. Choice B is incorrect. The past perfect verb “had gotten” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verbs used to describe the Sherpas and their activities. Choice C is incorrect. The past tense verb “got” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verbs used to describe the Sherpas and their activities. Choice D is incorrect. The past progressive verb “were getting” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verbs used to describe the Sherpas and their activities.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "947b3eb4","Question": "On July 23, 1854, a clipper ship called the Flying Cloud entered San Francisco ______ left New York Harbor under the guidance of Captain Josiah Perkins Creesy and his wife, navigator Eleanor Creesy, a mere 89 days and 8 hours earlier, the celebrated ship set a record that would stand for 135 years. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Bay and having","B": "y. Having","C": "Bay, having","D": "Bay having","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period after “Bay” is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence (“On…Bay”) and another sentence that begins with a supplementary phrase (“Having…years”). Here, the supplementary phrase beginning with “having” modiﬁes the subject of the second sentence, “the celebrated ship.” Choice A is incorrect. Without a comma preceding it, the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to join sentences. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to join two sentences. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences (“On…Bay” and “having…years”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "9484a870","Question": "From afar, African American ﬁber artist Bisa Butler’s portraits look like paintings, their depictions of human faces, bodies, and clothing so intricate that it seems only a ﬁne brush could have rendered them. When viewed up close, however, the portraits reveal themselves to be ______ stitching barely visible among the thousands of pieces of printed, microcut fabric. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "quilts, and the","B": "quilts, the","C": "quilts; the","D": "quilts. The","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between a main clause and a supplementary phrase. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the main clause (“the portraits...quilts”) and the supplementary noun phrase (“the stitching...fabric”) that provides a further description of how the portraits can be identiﬁed as quilts. Choice A is incorrect. A comma and the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to join a main clause and a supplementary noun phrase. Choice C is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join a main clause and a supplementary noun phrase. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with “the stitching.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "9553394d","Question": "In 1959, the ﬁlm industry debuted Smell-O-Vision. Theaters were ﬁtted with specialized vents that emitted odors at speciﬁc points in a ______ as the scent of roses when roses appeared in a scene. Smell-O-Vision failed to impress, however, with one reviewer declaring it “brieﬂy weird and not very interesting.” Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "movie such","B": "movie; such","C": "movie. Such","D": "movie, such","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The comma appropriately separates the nonessential descriptive aside 'such as…scene' from the independent clause 'Theaters were…movie.' Since the descriptive example of roses isn’t necessary for the sentence to function, it needs to be set off with punctuation. Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence. Since the example of roses isn’t necessary for the sentence to function, the descriptive aside 'such as…scene' needs to be separated from the preceding independent clause with some sort of punctuation. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. A semicolon can only be used to separate two independent clauses, but 'such…scene' is not an independent clause and couldn’t stand on its own as a sentence. Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a sentence fragment. The descriptive aside 'Such…scene' is not an independent clause and can’t stand on its own as a sentence.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "9621804c","Question": "Emperor Ashoka ruled the Maurya Empire in South Asia from roughly 270 to 232 BCE. He is known for enforcing a moral code called the Law of Piety, which established the sanctity of animal ______ the just treatment of the elderly, and the abolition of the slave trade. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "life","B": "life;","C": "life:","D": "life,","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. Notice that 'the sanctity of animal life' is the ﬁrst item in a list of three things. We must use a comma to separate the ﬁrst two items in the list, just as a comma is used to separate 'the just treatment of the elderly' and 'the abolition of the slave trade.' Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. Notice that 'the sanctity of animal life' is the ﬁrst item in a list of three things. To appropriately format the list, we need punctuation to separate each item. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. Notice that 'the sanctity of animal life' is the ﬁrst item in a list of three things. While semicolons are sometimes used to separate list items, this list uses commas to separate the other list items, and lists must use the same punctuation throughout. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. Notice that 'the sanctity of animal life' is the ﬁrst item in a list of three things. While colons can be used to introduce lists, they can’t be used to separate items within a list.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "96683dd3","Question": "The forty-seven geothermal springs of Arkansas’ Hot Springs National Park are sourced via a process known as natural groundwater recharge, in which rainwater percolates downward through the earth—in this case, the porous rocks of the hills around Hot ______ collect in a subterranean basin. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Springs to","B": "Springs: to","C": "Springs—to","D": "Springs, to","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary element within a sentence. The dash after “Springs” pairs with the dash after “earth” to separate the supplementary element “in this case, the porous rocks of the hills around Hot Springs” from the rest of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice B is incorrect because a colon can’t be paired with a dash in this way to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice D is incorrect because a comma can’t be paired with a dash in this way to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "97fa4431","Question": "To humans, it does not appear that the golden orb-weaver spider uses camouﬂage to capture its ______ the brightly colored arachnid seems to wait conspicuously in the center of its large circular web for insects to approach. Researcher Po Peng of the University of Melbourne has explained that the spider’s distinctive coloration may in fact be part of its appeal. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "prey, rather,","B": "prey rather,","C": "prey, rather;","D": "prey; rather,","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. The semicolon is correctly used to join the ﬁrst main clause (“To humans…prey”) and the second main clause (“rather… approach”). Further, the comma after the adverb “rather” is correctly used to separate the adverb from the main clause (“the brightly…approach”) it modiﬁes, logically indicating that the information in this clause (how the spider’s behavior appears to humans) is contrary to the information in the previous clause (how the spider’s behavior does not appear to humans). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without appropriate punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice C is incorrect. Placing the comma between the ﬁrst main clause “To humans…prey” and the adverb “rather” illogically indicates that the information in the ﬁrst main clause is contrary to what came before, which doesn’t make sense in this context.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "9890fee4","Question": "During the English neoclassical period (1660–1789), many writers imitated the epic poetry and satires of ancient Greece and Rome. They were not the ﬁrst in England to adopt the literary modes of classical ______ some of the most prominent ﬁgures of the earlier Renaissance period were also inﬂuenced by ancient Greek and Roman literature. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "antiquity, however","B": "antiquity, however,","C": "antiquity, however;","D": "antiquity; however,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary phrase following a clause. This choice uses a comma to separate the supplementary adverb phrase “however” from the independent clause it modiﬁes (“They …antiquity”) and uses a semicolon to join the ﬁrst independent clause (“They …antiquity”) and the second independent clause (“some…literature”). Further, placing the semicolon after “however” indicates that the information in the clause that this part of (that neoclassical writers were not the ﬁrst to adopt classical literary modes) is contrary to what might be assumed from the information in the previous sentence (that the neoclassical writers were unique in imitating classical epic poetry and satires). Choice A is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary after “however” between the two independent clauses with appropriate punctuation. Choice B is incorrect because the comma after “however” can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between the two independent clauses. Choice D is incorrect because placing the semicolon after “antiquity” illogically indicates that the information in the clause that this part of (that prominent Renaissance ﬁgures were also inﬂuenced by classical literature) is contrary to the information in the previous clause (that neoclassical writers were not the ﬁrst to adopt classical literary modes).","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "9a16780e","Question": "Inventor John Friedman created a prototype of the ﬁrst ﬂexible straw by inserting a screw into a paper straw and, using dental ﬂoss, binding the straw tightly around the ______ When the ﬂoss and screw were removed, the resulting corrugations in the paper allowed the straw to bend easily over the edge of a glass. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "screw’s thread’s.","B": "screws’ threads.","C": "screw’s threads.","D": "screws threads’.","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of plural and possessive nouns. The singular possessive noun “screw’s” and the plural noun “threads” correctly indicate that there is only one screw and it has multiple threads. Choice A is incorrect because the context requires the plural noun “threads,” not the singular possessive noun “thread’s.” Choice B is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive noun “screw’s,” not the plural possessive noun “screws’.” Choice D is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive noun “screw’s” and the plural noun “threads,” not the plural noun “screws” or the plural possessive noun “threads.’”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "9bb47a46","Question": "Humans were long thought to have begun occupying the Peruvian settlement of Machu Picchu between 1440 and 1450 CE. However, a team led by anthropologist Dr. Richard Burger used accelerator mass spectrometry to uncover evidence that it was occupied ______ 1420 CE, according to Burger, humans were likely inhabiting the area. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "earlier. In","B": "earlier, in","C": "earlier, which in","D": "earlier in","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence (“However...earlier”) and another (“In...area”). The supplementary phrase “in 1420 CE” modiﬁes “humans,” the subject of the third sentence. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Moreover, the subordinating conjunction “which” creates a confusing and illogical sentence that suggests that the supplementary phrase beginning with “in” modiﬁes the previous information (“However...earlier”) rather than the information that follows. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences (“However...earlier” and “in...area”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "9ca600ea","Question": "According to Naomi Nakayama of the University of Edinburgh, the reason seeds from a dying dandelion appear to ﬂoat in the air while ______ is that their porous plumes enhance drag, allowing the seeds to stay airborne long enough for the wind to disperse them throughout the surrounding area. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "falling,","B": "falling:","C": "falling;","D": "falling","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The word “falling” occurs in the middle of a clause and isn’t part of a supplement, so we don’t need any punctuation after it. We can see this more clearly if we simplify the rest of the sentence: “The reason seeds appear to ﬂoat while falling is that their plumes enhance drag.” . Choice A is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. The word “falling” occurs in the middle of a clause and isn’t part of a supplement, so we don’t need any punctuation after it. We can see this more clearly if we simplify the sentence: “The reason seeds appear to ﬂoat while falling is that their plumes enhance drag.” . Choice B is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. The word “falling” occurs in the middle of a clause and isn’t part of a supplement, so we don’t need any punctuation after it. We can see this more clearly if we simplify the sentence: “The reason seeds appear to ﬂoat while falling is that their plumes enhance drag.” . Choice C is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. The word “falling” occurs in the middle of a clause and isn’t part of a supplement, so we don’t need any punctuation after it. We can see this more clearly if we simplify the sentence: “The reason seeds appear to ﬂoat while falling is that their plumes enhance drag.” .","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "9cda7487","Question": "American writer Edwidge Danticat, who emigrated from Haiti in 1981, has won acclaim for her powerful short stories, novels, and ______ her lyrical yet unﬂinching depictions of her native country’s turbulent history, writer Robert Antoni has compared Danticat to Nobel Prize–winning novelist Toni Morrison. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "essays, praising","B": "essays and praising","C": "essays praising","D": "essays. Praising","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period after “essays” is used correctly to mark the boundary between one sentence (“American…essays”) and another (“praising… Morrison”). The participial phrase beginning with “Praising” modiﬁes the subject of the second sentence, “writer Robert Antoni.” Choice A is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice B is incorrect. Without a comma preceding it, the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to join sentences. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The sentences (“American…essays” and “Praising…Morrison”) are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "9d68950c","Question": "Po’Pay was a Tewa leader from Ohkay Owingeh, a pueblo located about twenty-ﬁve miles north of present-day Santa Fe, New Mexico. He was instrumental in organizing the Pueblo Revolt of ______ as a result of his leadership, the Spanish colonizers were expelled from the region for a time. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "1680","B": "1680 and","C": "1680,","D": "1680, and","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. This choice correctly uses a comma and the coordinating conjunction “and” to join the ﬁrst main clause (“He…1680”) and the second main clause (“as…time”). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice B is incorrect because when coordinating two longer main clauses such as these, it’s conventional to use a comma before the coordinating conjunction. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "9dbd2461","Question": "In 2015, a team led by materials scientists Anirudha Sumant and Diana Berman succeeded in reducing the coeﬃcient of friction (COF) between two surfaces to the lowest possible level—superlubricity. A nearly frictionless (and, as its name suggests, extremely slippery) state, ______ Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "when their COF drops below 0.01, two surfaces reach superlubricity.","B": "two surfaces, when their COF drops below 0.01, reach superlubricity.","C": "reaching superlubricity occurs when two surfaces’ F drops below 0.01.","D": "superlubricity is reached when two surfaces’ COF drops below 0.01.","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The subject of the modiﬁer “a nearly frictionless state” is “superlubricity.” Subject-modiﬁer placement requires a modiﬁer and its subject to be next to one another, so “superlubricity” must be the ﬁrst word in the missing clause. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a subject-modiﬁer placement error. The subject of the modiﬁer “a nearly frictionless state” is “superlubricity.” Subject-modiﬁer placement requires a modiﬁer and its subject to be next to one another, so “superlubricity” must be the ﬁrst word in the missing clause. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a subject-modiﬁer placement error. The subject of the modiﬁer “a nearly frictionless state” is “superlubricity.” Subject-modiﬁer placement requires a modiﬁer and its subject to be next to one another, so “superlubricity” must be the ﬁrst word in the missing clause. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a subject-modiﬁer placement error. The subject of the modiﬁer “a nearly frictionless state” is “superlubricity.” Subject-modiﬁer placement requires a modiﬁer and its subject to be next to one another, so “superlubricity” must be the ﬁrst word in the missing clause.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "9ed077ff","Question": "The radiation that ______ during the decay of radioactive atomic nuclei is known as gamma radiation. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "occurs","B": "have occurred","C": "occur","D": "are occurring","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb 'occurs' agrees in number with the singular subject 'radiation.' Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb 'have occurred' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'radiation.' Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb 'occur' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'radiation.' Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb 'are occurring' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'radiation.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "a068eea7","Question": "While many video game creators strive to make their graphics ever more ______ others look to the past, developing titles with visuals inspired by the “8-bit” games of the 1980s and 1990s. (The term “8-bit” refers to a console whose processor could only handle eight bits of data at once.) Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "lifelike but","B": "lifelike","C": "lifelike,","D": "lifelike, but","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a subordinate clause and a main clause. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the subordinate clause (“While…lifelike”) and the main clause (“others look to the past”). Choice A is incorrect because it results in an incomplete sentence with no main clause. Choice B is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the subordinate clause (“While…lifelike”) and the main clause (“others…past”). Choice D is incorrect because it results in an incomplete sentence with no main clause.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "a1d5e1d3","Question": "Archaeologists have estimated that the pre-Columbian Native American city of Cahokia, located across the Mississippi River from modern-day St. Louis, Missouri, had as many as 20,000 inhabitants in the year 1150 ______ it one of the largest cities in North America at the time. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "CE making","B": "CE. Making","C": ", making","D": "CE; making","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The phrase “making…at the time” provides additional information about Cahokia that’s not required for the sentence to make sense or function grammatically. As a nonessential supplement, this phrase should be separated from the rest of the sentence with a comma. Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence. The nonessential descriptive aside “making…at the time” needs to be separated from the rest of the sentence with a comma. Choice B is incorrect. This choice results in a sentence fragment. “Making…at the time” doesn’t have a subject and can’t stand on its own as a sentence. Thus, it can’t be separated from the rest of the sentence with a period. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error. “Making…at the time” doesn’t have a subject and can’t stand on its own as an independent clause. Since a semicolon can only link two independent clauses, using one here creates an error.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "a1e6e266","Question": "The Alvarez theory, developed in 1980 by physicist Luis Walter Alvarez and his geologist son Walter Alvarez, maintained that the secondary effects of an asteroid impact caused many dinosaurs and other animals to die ______ it left unexplored the question of whether unrelated volcanic activity might have also contributed to the mass extinctions. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "out but","B": "out, but","C": "out","D": "out,","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. This choice correctly uses a comma and the coordinating conjunction “but” to join the ﬁrst main clause (“the Alvarez…out”) and the second main clause (“it left…extinctions”). Choice A is incorrect because when coordinating two longer main clauses such as these, it’s conventional to use a comma before the coordinating conjunction. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "a660d91a","Question": "Food and the sensation of taste are central to Monique Truong’s novels. In The Book of Salt, for example, the exiled character of Bình connects to his native Saigon through the food he prepares, while in Bitter in the Mouth, the character of Linda ______ a form of synesthesia whereby the words she hears evoke tastes. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "experienced","B": "had experienced","C": "experiences","D": "will be experiencing","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense. In this choice, the present tense verb “experiences” is consistent with the other present tense verbs (e.g., “connects” and “prepares”) used to describe the events in Truong’s novels. Furthermore, it’s conventional to use the present tense when discussing a literary work. Choice A is incorrect because the past tense verb “experienced” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verbs used to describe the events in Truong’s novels. Choice B is incorrect because the past perfect tense verb “had experienced” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verbs used to describe the events in Truong’s novels. Choice D is incorrect because the future progressive tense verb “will be experiencing” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verbs used to describe the events in Truong’s novels.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "a8c1d1b9","Question": "“Praise Song for the Day,” Elizabeth Alexander’s 2009 inaugural poem, asserts that “We cross dirt roads and highways…to see what’s on the other side.” Alexander’s use of “we” ______ Americans’ collective efforts and shared desire to seek new opportunity. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "evokes","B": "are evoking","C": "have evoked","D": "evoke","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb 'evokes' agrees in number with the singular subject 'Alexander’s use.' Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb 'are evoking' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'Alexander’s use.' Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb 'have evoked' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'Alexander’s use.' Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb 'evoke' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'Alexander’s use.'","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "a95ae2b8","Question": "Working from an earlier discovery of Charpentier’s, chemists Emmanuelle Charpentier and Jennifer Doudna—winners of the 2020 Nobel Prize in Chemistry—re-created and then reprogrammed the so-called “genetic scissors” of a species of DNA- cleaving bacteria ______ a tool that is revolutionizing the ﬁeld of gene technology. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "to forge","B": "forging","C": "forged","D": "and forging","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of ﬁnite and nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. The nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to forge” is correctly used to form a nonﬁnite (inﬁnitive) clause that explains why the chemists re- created and reprogrammed the DNA-cleaving bacteria. Choice B is incorrect. Without a comma separating the main clause (“chemists...bacteria”) from the participle “forging,” this choice illogically suggests that the bacteria are forging a tool, which doesn’t make sense. Choice C is incorrect. Without a coordinating conjunction such as “and” placed before it, the ﬁnite past tense verb “forged” can’t be used in this way to describe the chemists’ actions. Choice D is incorrect. If read as a ﬁnite verb, the present progressive verb “forging” isn’t consistent with the past tense verbs used in this sentence to describe the actions of the chemists. If read as a nonﬁnite verb, the participle “forging” can’t be used in this way because there is no following main clause for it to modify.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "a9616eac","Question": "In crafting her fantasy ﬁction, Nigerian-born British author Helen Oyeyemi has drawn inspiration from the classic nineteenth- century fairy tales of the Brothers Grimm. Her 2014 novel Boy, Snow, Bird, for instance, is a complex retelling of the story of Snow White, while her 2019 novel ______ offers a delicious twist on the classic tale of Hansel and Gretel. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Gingerbread—","B": "Gingerbread,","C": "Gingerbread","D": "Gingerbread:","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a subject and a verb. When, as in this case, a subject (“her 2019 novel Gingerbread”) is immediately followed by a verb (“offers”), no punctuation is needed. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "ac384264","Question": "Wanda Diaz-Merced is an astrophysicist who lost her sight when she was young. Diaz-Merced’s condition inspired her to develop software that can translate scientiﬁc data into sound. Sound-based tools ______ scientists to detect subtle patterns in data. Such patterns may not be evident in traditional graphs. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "has enabled","B": "enable","C": "is enabling","D": "enables","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The plural verb 'enable' agrees in number with the plural subject 'sound-based tools.' Choice A is incorrect because the singular verb 'has enabled' doesn’t agree in number with the plural subject 'sound-based tools.' Choice C is incorrect because the singular verb 'is enabling' doesn’t agree in number with the plural subject 'sound- based tools.' Choice D is incorrect because the singular verb 'enables' doesn’t agree in number with the plural subject 'sound-based tools.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "ac4b2c70","Question": "Obsidian is a kind of volcanic glass formed when lava cools so quickly that the atoms inside it cannot arrange themselves in a crystalline structure. You ______ more about obsidian’s structure, which is classiﬁed as amorphous, in a later chapter. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "had learned","B": "had been learning","C": "will learn","D": "have learned","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense in a sentence. In this choice, the future tense verb “will learn,” used in conjunction with the phrase “in a later chapter,” correctly indicates that “you” (the reader) are going to learn about obsidian’s structure at some point in the future. Choice A is incorrect because the past perfect verb “had learned” doesn’t indicate that the subject is going to learn about obsidian’s structure in the future. Choice B is incorrect because the past perfect progressive verb “had been learning” doesn’t indicate that the subject is going to learn about obsidian’s structure in the future. Choice D is incorrect because the present perfect verb “have learned” doesn’t indicate that the subject is going to learn about obsidian’s structure in the future.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "ad1825e8","Question": "In 1976, the Inuit rock group Sikumiut recorded the album People of the Ice. Though only their ﬁrst record, it shows a band already skilled at the diﬃcult task of making music that sounds easy and fun. On songs like “Utirumavunga,” Lucassie Koperqualuk’s guitar riffs effortlessly ______ Charlie Adams’s delightfully catchy vocal melodies. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "blend, with","B": "blend. With","C": "blend; with","D": "blend with","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a verb and a prepositional phrase. No punctuation is needed between the verb “blend” and the prepositional phrase “with Charlie Adams’s delightfully catchy vocal melodies.” The prepositional phrase completes the idea of the sentence, explaining with what Koperqualuk’s guitar riffs blend. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and the prepositional phrase. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and the prepositional phrase. Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the verb and the prepositional phrase.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "ada2e61b","Question": "In order to prevent nonnative ﬁsh species from moving freely between the Mediterranean and Red Seas, marine biologist Bella Galil has proposed that a saline lock system be installed along the Suez Canal in Egypt’s Great Bitter Lakes. The lock would increase the salinity of the lakes and ______ a natural barrier of water most marine creatures would be unable to cross. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "creates","B": "create","C": "creating","D": "created","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of non-ﬁnite (untensed) verb forms in a sentence. The modal “would,” which indicates the future from a perspective in the past, should be accompanied by a non-ﬁnite plain form verb. In this choice, the non-ﬁnite plain form verb “create” is used correctly in conjunction with the non-ﬁnite plain form verb “increase” to describe what the lock would do. Choice A is incorrect because the ﬁnite present tense verb “creates” can’t be used in this way with the modal “would” to describe what the lock would do. Choice C is incorrect because the present participle “creating” can’t be used in this way with the modal “would” to describe what the lock would do. Choice D is incorrect because the ﬁnite past tense verb “created” can’t be used in this way with the modal “would” to describe what the lock would do.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "ae4d8cb0","Question": "The violins handmade in the seventeeth century by Italian craftsman Antonio Stradivari have been celebrated as some of the ﬁnest in the world. In close collaboration with musicians, Stradivari introduced changes to the shape of a traditional violin, ﬂattening some of the instrument’s curves and making ______ lighter overall. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "those","B": "one","C": "them","D": "it","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is pronoun–antecedent agreement. The singular pronoun “it” agrees in number with the singular antecedent “violin” and thus indicates that the traditional violin (and not its curves) was made lighter. Choice A is incorrect because the plural pronoun “those” doesn’t agree in number with the singular antecedent “violin.” Choice B is incorrect because the singular pronoun “one” is ambiguous in this context; the resulting sentence leaves unclear what Stradivari made lighter. Choice C is incorrect because the plural pronoun “them” doesn’t agree in number with the singular antecedent “violin.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "ae669b46","Question": "Formed in 1967 to foster political and economic stability within the Asia-Paciﬁc region, the Association of Southeast Asian Nations was originally made up of ﬁve members: Thailand, the Philippines, Singapore, Malaysia, and Indonesia. By the end of the 1990s, the organization ______ its initial membership. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "has doubled","B": "had doubled","C": "doubles","D": "will double","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense. In this choice, the past perfect verb “had doubled” properly indicates that the doubling of the organization’s initial membership occurred during a speciﬁc period before the present (between the organization’s founding in 1967 and the end of the 1990s). Choice A is incorrect because the present perfect verb “has doubled” doesn’t indicate that the organization’s doubling of its initial membership occurred during a speciﬁc period in the past. Choice C is incorrect because the present tense verb “doubles” doesn’t indicate that the organization’s doubling of its initial membership occurred during a speciﬁc period in the past. Choice D is incorrect because the future tense verb “will double” doesn’t indicate that the organization’s doubling of its initial membership occurred during a speciﬁc period in the past.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "aef7c55f","Question": "Eli Eisenberg, a genetics expert at Tel Aviv University in Israel, recently discovered that ______ have a special genetic ability called RNA editing that confers evolutionary advantages. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "cephalopods, ocean dwellers that include the squid, the octopus, and the cuttleﬁsh","B": "cephalopods—ocean dwellers—that include the squid, the octopus, and the cuttleﬁsh,","C": "cephalopods, ocean dwellers that include: the squid, the octopus, and the cuttleﬁsh,","D": "cephalopods—ocean dwellers that include the squid, the octopus, and the cuttleﬁsh—","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary element within a sentence. In this choice, the dash after “cephalopods” pairs with the dash after “cuttleﬁsh” to clearly separate the supplementary element “ocean dwellers that include the squid, the octopus, and the cuttleﬁsh” from the rest of the sentence. This supplementary element functions to explain what cephalopds are, and the pair of dashes indicates that this element could be removed without affecting the grammatical coherence of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element that explains what cephalopods are from the rest of the sentence. Choice B is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element that explains what cephalopods are from the rest of the sentence. Choice C is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element that explains what cephalopods are from the rest of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "af545187","Question": "In 1930, Japanese American artist Chiura Obata depicted the natural beauty of Yosemite National Park in two memorable woodcuts: Evening at Carl Inn and Lake Basin in the High Sierra. In 2019, ______ exhibited alongside 150 of Obata’s other works in a single-artist show at the Smithsonian American Art Museum. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "it was","B": "they were","C": "this was","D": "some were","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is pronoun–antecedent agreement. The plural pronoun “they” agrees in number with the plural antecedent “woodcuts” and clearly identiﬁes what was exhibited at the Smithsonian American Art Museum. Choice A is incorrect because the singular pronoun “it” doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent “woodcuts.” Choice C is incorrect because the singular pronoun “this” doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent “woodcuts.” Choice D is incorrect because the plural pronoun “some” is illogical in this context (referring to “some” of two woodcuts).","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "b17585b1","Question": "Public-awareness campaigns about the need to reduce single-use plastics can be successful, says researcher Kim Borg of Monash University in Australia, when these campaigns give consumers a choice: for example, Japan achieved a 40 percent reduction in plastic-bag use after cashiers were instructed to ask customers whether ______ wanted a bag. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "they","B": "one","C": "you","D": "it","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is pronoun–antecedent agreement. The plural pronoun “they” agrees in number with the plural antecedent “customers.” Choice B is incorrect because the singular pronoun “one” doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent “customers.” Choice C is incorrect because the second person pronoun “you” isn’t conventional as a substitute for “customers.” It suggests that the audience (“you”) is the customer. Choice D is incorrect because the singular pronoun “it” doesn’t agree in number with the plural antecedent “customers.”","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "b36a623e","Question": "The Progressive Era in the United States witnessed the rise of numerous Black women’s clubs, local organizations that advocated for racial and gender equality. Among the clubs’ leaders ______ Josephine St. Pierre Ruﬃn, founder of the Women’s Era Club of Boston. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "was","B": "were","C": "are","D": "have been","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested here is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb “was” agrees in number with the singular subject “Josephine St. Pierre Ruﬃn.” Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb “were” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “Josephine St. Pierre Ruﬃn.” Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb “are” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “Josephine St. Pierre Ruﬃn.” Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb “have been” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “Josephine St. Pierre Ruﬃn.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "b64dbd3f","Question": "Human-made (synthetic) ﬁbers used in clothes and many other consumer products are more durable than most natural plant ______ the manufacture of synthetic ﬁbers requires toxic chemical solvents that can pollute air and water. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "ﬁbers,","B": "ﬁbers but","C": "ﬁbers","D": "ﬁbers, but","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the coordination of main clauses within a sentence. This choice correctly uses a comma and the coordinating conjunction “but” to join the ﬁrst main clause (“Human-made...ﬁbers”) and the second main clause (“the manufacture...water”). Choice A is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. Without a conjunction following it, a comma can’t be used in this way to join two main clauses. Choice B is incorrect because when coordinating two longer main clauses such as these, it’s conventional to use a comma before the coordinating conjunction. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a run-on sentence. The two main clauses are fused without punctuation and/or a conjunction.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "b670ec9d","Question": "A study led by scientist Rebecca Kirby at the University of Wisconsin–Madison found that black bears that eat human food before hibernation have increased levels of a rare carbon isotope, ______ due to the higher C levels in corn and cane sugar. Bears with these elevated levels were also found to have much shorter hibernation periods on average. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "carbon-13, ( C) 13","B": "carbon-13 ( C) 13","C": "carbon-13, ( , 13","D": "carbon-13 ( C), 13","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary element within a sentence. The comma after “(13C)” pairs with the comma after “isotope” to separate the supplementary element “carbon-13 (13C)” from the rest of the sentence. This supplementary element deﬁnes the “rare carbon isotope,” and the pair of commas indicates that this element could be removed without affecting the grammatical coherence of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element “carbon-13 (13C)” from the rest of the sentence. Choice B is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element “carbon-13 (13C)” from the rest of the sentence. Choice C is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the supplementary element “carbon-13 (13C)” from the rest of the sentence. The comma after “carbon-13” isn’t necessary because the parentheses around “13C” already separate this element from the rest of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "b818ba13","Question": "In 1637, the price of tulips skyrocketed in Amsterdam, with single bulbs of rare varieties selling for up to the equivalent of $200,000 in today’s US dollars. Some historians ______ that this “tulip mania” was the ﬁrst historical instance of an asset bubble, which occurs when investors drive prices to highs not supported by actual demand. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "claiming","B": "claim","C": "having claimed","D": "to claim","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of ﬁnite and nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. A main clause requires a ﬁnite verb to perform the action of the subject (in this case, “some historians”), and this choice supplies the ﬁnite present tense verb “claim” to indicate what some historians do. Choice A is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “claiming” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice C is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “having claimed” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice D is incorrect because the nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to claim” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "bafad0f0","Question": "Ten of William Shakespeare’s plays are classiﬁed as histories. Although each one of these plays, which include Henry V and Richard III, ______ on a single historical ﬁgure (speciﬁcally, an English king), some, such as Henry VI Part One and Henry VI Part Two, feature different episodes from the same monarch’s life. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "focuses","B": "focus","C": "are focused","D": "were focused","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb 'focuses' agrees in number with the singular subject 'each one of these plays,' which refers to each play individually. Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb 'focus' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'each one of these plays.' Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb 'are focused' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'each one of these plays.' Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb 'were focused' doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject 'each one of these plays.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "bbcd773b","Question": "When particles are suspended in liquid (like pollen in a water glass), they will zigzag randomly through the liquid and collide with one another in perpetuity. This type of random, continuous ______ is known as Brownian motion, can be observed throughout the natural world. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "movement: which","B": "movement, which","C": "movement which","D": "movement. Which","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. This choice correctly uses commas to set off the nonessential relative clause 'which is known as Brownian motion' that provides extra information about the 'random, continuous movement' that isn’t necessary for the function of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error. The relative clause 'which is known as Brownian motion' is a nonessential supplement. Nonessential supplements need to be set apart from the rest of the sentence with a pair of commas, dashes, or parentheses, so we can’t use a colon here. Also, notice that colons can only come after an independent clause, which isn’t the case here. Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error. The relative clause 'which is known as Brownian motion' is a nonessential supplement, so it should be separated from the rest of the sentence by a pair of matching punctuation marks. We already have a comma after 'motion,' so we need to add a comma before 'which.' This choice is missing that comma. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a sentence fragment. 'This type of random, continuous movement' is not an independent clause and can’t stand alone as a full sentence, so we can’t put a period here.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "bceb20a7","Question": "Psychophysicist Howard Moskowitz was hired by a soda company to determine how much artiﬁcial sweetener ______ After conducting consumer taste tests, he found that no such ideal existed: participants expressed a wide range of preferences for different blends of sweetener, carbonization, and ﬂavoring. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "do most people prefer in a diet drink?","B": "do most people prefer in a diet drink.","C": "most people prefer in a diet drink?","D": "most people prefer in a diet drink.","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. This sentence is a statement: “Moskowitz was hired by a soda company to determine how much artiﬁcial sweetener most people prefer in a diet drink.” So a period is the most appropriate punctuation mark. Choice A is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. This sentence is not a question—it’s a statement. So a question mark is not the appropriate punctuation. Choice B is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. We already have the verbs “was hired…to determine” in this sentence. The verb “do” is not needed and results in a confusing, ungrammatical sentence. Choice C is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. This sentence is not a question—it’s a statement. So a question mark is not the appropriate punctuation.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "bd9ef66d","Question": "In 1727, dramatist Lewis Theobald presented a new play, Double Falsehood, at a London theater. Theobald claimed that his drama was based on a little-known play by William Shakespeare, Cardenio. Many, including poet Alexander Pope, were ______ historians have determined that Shakespeare’s company did perform a play called Cardenio in 1613. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "skeptical but","B": "skeptical, but","C": "skeptical,","D": "skeptical","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. There are two independent clauses in the sentence, each with a subject and a verb: 'many...were skeptical' and 'historians have determined….' These clauses can be grammatically joined by a comma and the coordinating conjunction 'but.' Choice A is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence, which occurs when two independent clauses are joined without punctuation. Two independent clauses can’t be joined by just the coordinating conjunction 'but.' A comma would also be required. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error called a comma splice. This sentence contains two independent clauses ('Many…were skeptical' and 'historians have determined…'). A comma alone can’t join two independent clauses. That requires a comma and a coordinating conjunction. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a run-on sentence, which occurs when two independent clauses are joined without punctuation. This sentence contains two independent clauses ('Many…were skeptical' and 'historians have determined…'), which need to be either joined by a semicolon, joined by a comma and a coordinating conjunction, or separated by a period.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "be3725e6","Question": "Each year in the fall, when the weather starts to cool in the northern hemisphere, millions of North American monarch butterﬂies journey south. Searching for food and warmer habitats, they ______ thousands of miles—from as far north as Canada all the way down to Mexico—on this annual migration. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "ﬂew","B": "were ﬂying","C": "had ﬂown","D": "ﬂy","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense. In this choice, the present tense verb “ﬂy” is consistent with the other present tense verb ( “journey”) used to describe the butterﬂies’ yearly migration. Together, these simple present tense verbs correctly indicate that the migration is a current, yearly occurrence. Choice A is incorrect. The simple past tense verb “ﬂew” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verb used to describe the butterﬂies’ yearly migration. Choice B is incorrect. The past progressive tense verb “were ﬂying” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verb used to describe the butterﬂies’ yearly migration. Choice C is incorrect. The past perfect tense verb “had ﬂown” isn’t consistent with the other present tense verb used to describe the butterﬂies’ yearly migration.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "be3760db","Question": "In 1994, almost 200 years after the death of Wang Zhenyi, the International Astronomical ______ the contributions of the barrier-breaking 18th-century astronomer and author of “Dispute of the Procession of the Equinoxes,” naming a crater on Venus after her. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Union would ﬁnally acknowledge","B": "Union to ﬁnally acknowledge","C": "Union, having ﬁnally acknowledged","D": "Union, ﬁnally acknowledging","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. It’s the only choice that offers a form of the verb “acknowledge” that can go with the subject “International Astronomical Union” to make a complete sentence. This might seem like an odd use of “would,” but when speaking from a point of view in the past, we can actually use “would” to express something that happened later. That’s the case here: 200 years after Wang Zhenyi’s death, the IAU would ﬁnally acknowledge her contributions. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a sentence fragment. There’s no main verb elsewhere in the sentence, so we need a form of the verb “acknowledge” that can go with the subject “the International Astronomical Union” and serve as that main verb. “To acknowledge” can’t do that. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a sentence fragment. There’s no main verb elsewhere in the sentence, so we need a form of the verb “acknowledge” that can go with the subject “the International Astronomical Union” and serve as that main verb. “Having acknowledged” can’t do that. Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a sentence fragment. There’s no main verb elsewhere in the sentence, so we need a form of the verb “acknowledge” that can go with the subject “the International Astronomical Union” and serve as that main verb. The “-ing” form can’t do that.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "be7f8398","Question": "To serve local families during the Great Depression, innovative New York City librarian Pura Belpré offered storytelling in both English and Spanish, an uncommon ______ celebrated el Día de los Tres Reyes Magos, an important community holiday; and put on puppet shows dramatizing Puerto Rican folktales. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "practice, at the time","B": "practice at the time;","C": "practice, at the time,","D": "practice at the time,","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of elements in a complex series. It’s conventional to use a semicolon to separate items in a complex series with internal punctuation, and in this choice, the semicolon after 'time' is conventionally used to separate the ﬁrst item ('offered…time') and the second ('celebrated… holiday') in the series of activities that librarian Pura Belpré offered. Moreover, the semicolon after 'time' matches the semicolon used later to separate the second item ('celebrated...holiday') and the third ('and...folktales') in the series. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the ﬁrst item and the second item in the complex series. Furthermore, a comma isn’t needed between the noun 'practice' and the prepositional phrase 'at the time' because the prepositional phrase is essential to the full meaning of the phrase 'an uncommon practice at the time.' Choice C is incorrect because a comma after 'time' doesn’t match the semicolon used later to separate the second ('celebrated...holiday') and third ('and...folktales') items in the series. Furthermore, a comma isn’t needed between the noun 'practice' and the prepositional phrase 'at the time' because the prepositional phrase is essential to the full meaning of the phrase 'an uncommon practice at the time.' Choice D is incorrect because a comma after 'time' doesn’t match the semicolon used later to separate the second ('celebrated...holiday') and third ('and...folktales') items in the series.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "bff697dd","Question": "The alga species Chlorella vulgaris is very eﬃcient at making oxygen. For this reason, scientists are currently exploring ways to use this species in space. C. vulgaris might be used, for example, to build future biological air exchange systems that ______ oxygen for astronauts. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "are producing","B": "produced","C": "produce","D": "have produced","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense. Simple present tense verbs can be used to describe actions that tend to occur, including in a hypothetical or future scenario. In this case, the simple present tense verb “produce” indicates what the air exchange systems might be able to do in the future (produce oxygen for astronauts). Choice A is incorrect. The present progressive tense verb “are producing” suggests that the oxygen is currently being produced, not that it might be produced in the future. Choice B is incorrect because the past tense verb “produced” suggests that the oxygen was produced in the past, not that it might be produced in the future. Choice D is incorrect because the present perfect tense verb “have produced” suggests that the oxygen has been produced from a point in the past up to the present, not that it might be produced in the future.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "c04927f2","Question": "In the canon of North African literature, Moroccan author Driss Chraïbi’s 1954 novel The Simple Past (Le Passé simple) looms large. A coming-of-age story, a social meditation, and a sober gaze into the dark maw of French colonialism, ______ interrogates systemic power with memorable intensity. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Morocco gained its independence two years before the publication of Chraïbi’s debut novel, which","B": "Chraïbi’s debut novel, published two years before Morocco gained its independence,","C": "raïbi wrote a debut novel that, published two years before Morocco gained its independence,","D": "published two years before Morocco gained its independence, Chraïbi wrote a debut novel that","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. Subject-modiﬁer placement requires a modiﬁer and its subject to be next to each other. The subject of the modiﬁer 'a coming-of-age story…colonialism' is Chraïbi’s novel The Simple Past, so the subject 'Chraïbi’s debut novel' ﬁts perfectly after this introductory modifying phrase. Choice A is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The introductory modiﬁer 'a coming-of-age story…colonialism' is describing Chraïbi’s novel, not Morocco. However, this choice places Morocco directly next to that modiﬁer. Choice C is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The introductory modiﬁer 'a coming- of-age story…colonialism' all describes Chraïbi’s novel, not Chraïbi himself. However, this choice places Chraïbi directly next to that modiﬁer. Choice D is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The modiﬁer 'a coming-of- age story…' is describing Chraïbi’s novel, so that needs to be the subject immediately after the modiﬁer. This choice adds another modiﬁer that describes Chraïbi’s novel, but then puts 'Chraïbi' himself—not the novel—right after that modiﬁer, which doesn’t make sense. Chraïbi wasn’t 'published two years before' Moroccan independence; his novel The Simple Past was.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "c226133d","Question": "In 2016, engineer Vanessa Galvez oversaw the installation of 164 bioswales, vegetated channels designed to absorb and divert stormwater, along the streets of Queens, New York. By reducing the runoff ﬂowing into city sewers, ______ Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "the mitigation of both street ﬂooding and the resulting pollution of nearby waterways has been achieved by bioswales.","B": "the bioswales have mitigated both street ﬂooding and the resulting pollution of nearby waterways.","C": "the bioswales’ mitigation of both street ﬂooding and the resulting pollution of nearby waterways has been achieved.","D": "both street ﬂooding and the resulting pollution of nearby waterways have been mitigated by bioswales.","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice makes the noun phrase “the bioswales” the subject of the sentence and places it immediately after the modifying phrase “By reducing…sewers.” In doing so, this choice clearly establishes that the bioswales—and not another noun in the sentence—are reducing runoff ﬂowing into city sewers. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “the mitigation… waterways” immediately after the modifying phrase results in unclear modiﬁcation. The resulting sentence makes it hard to determine what is responsible for “reducing the runoff”: the bioswales or some other noun in the sentence. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “the bioswales’ mitigation…waterways” immediately after the modifying phrase results in unclear modiﬁcation. The resulting sentence makes it hard to determine what is responsible for “reducing the runoff”: the bioswales or some other noun in the sentence. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “street ﬂooding and the resulting pollution” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the “ﬂooding and pollution” are reducing runoff ﬂowing into city sewers.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "c4e083ae","Question": "On April 5, 1977, Kitty Cone and 150 other disability rights activists entered a San Francisco federal building. After pleading for years—to no effect—for the passage of key antidiscrimination legislation, ______ until their demands were addressed. Finally, on April 28, the legislation was signed. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "pressure on lawmakers increased when the activists staged a sit-in protest","B": "a sit-in protest staged by the activists increased pressure on lawmakers","C": "lawmakers came under increased pressure when the activists staged a sit-in protest","D": "the activists increased pressure on lawmakers by staging a sit-in protest","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice makes the noun phrase “the activists” the subject of the sentence and places it immediately after the modifying phrase “after...legislation.” In doing so, this choice clearly establishes that the activists—and not another noun in the sentence—were pleading for the passage of antidiscrimination legislation. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “pressure on lawmakers” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the “pressure” was pleading for the passage of antidiscrimination legislation. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “a sit-in protest” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the “protest” was pleading for the passage of antidiscrimination legislation. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “lawmakers” immediately after the modifying phrase suggests that “lawmakers” were pleading for the passage of antidiscrimination legislation. While it’s possible for lawmakers to plead for the passage of legislation, the context strongly suggests that it’s the activists who pleaded for years for the passage of antidiscrimination legislation.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "c657b510","Question": "When they were ﬁrst discovered in Australia in 1798, duck-billed, beaver-tailed platypuses so deﬁed categorization that one scientist assigned them the name Ornithorhynchus paradoxus: “paradoxical bird-snout.” The animal, which lays eggs but also nurses ______ young with milk, has since been classiﬁed as belonging to the monotremes group. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "they’re","B": "their","C": "its","D": "it’s","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The singular possessive pronoun 'its' agrees with the singular antecedent 'the animal' and indicates that the 'young' belong to it. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a pronoun-antecedent agreement error. 'They’re' is a contraction of 'they are,' a plural pronoun and verb, but the antecedent 'the animal' is singular. Also, we don’t need the extra verb 'are' — we already have a main verb in this clause, so adding 'are' would be confusing and ungrammatical. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a pronoun-antecedent agreement error. 'Their' is a plural pronoun, but the subject of the sentence is 'the animal,' a singular noun. Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a confusing and ungrammatical sentence. 'It’s' is a contraction for 'it is.' We already have the verb 'nurses' in this clause, so we shouldn’t add the verb 'is.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "c814e8b5","Question": "In 1881, French chemist Camille Faure redesigned the rechargeable lead-acid battery. Faure’s design greatly increased the amount of electricity that the original battery, which the French physicist Gaston Planté ______ ﬁfteen years earlier, could hold. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "is inventing","B": "will invent","C": "invents","D": "had invented","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. Faure redesigned the battery in 1881, and the original battery was invented “ﬁfteen years earlier.” Notice that this is the only choice in the past tense. To indicate that a past occurrence took place before another past occurrence, we need to use “had” + the past tense form of the verb. This is called the “past perfect” tense. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a tense error. Planté invented the original battery in the past, so we shouldn’t use the present tense “is inventing.” Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a tense error. Planté invented the original battery in the past, so we shouldn’t use the future tense “will invent.” Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a tense error. Planté invented the original battery in the past, so we shouldn’t use the present tense “invents.”","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "ca252d9a","Question": "After winning the 1860 presidential election, Abraham Lincoln appointed Edward Bates, Salmon P. Chase, and William H. Seward to his cabinet. Lincoln’s decision was surprising, since each of these men had run against him, but historians have praised it, noting that Lincoln ______ his rivals’ diverse talents to strengthen his administration. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "has leveraged","B": "is leveraging","C": "will leverage","D": "leveraged","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The subject of the verb is “Lincoln,” and the ﬁrst sentence tells us that we’re talking about something that Abraham Lincoln did in 1860. So the simple past tense “leveraged” ﬁts the logic of the text. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a tense issue. “Has leveraged” is the present perfect tense, which is used for an action that began in the past and continues into the present. Lincoln started leveraging his rivals’ talents in 1860—it’s deﬁnitely not still happening today. So the present perfect tense isn’t appropriate. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a tense issue. “Is leveraging” is the present tense, but Lincoln leveraged his rivals’ talents in 1860, so the present tense isn’t appropriate. Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a tense issue. “Will leverage” is the future tense, but Lincoln leveraged his rivals’ talents in 1860, so the future tense isn’t appropriate.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "cc9aebbd","Question": "The life spans of rockﬁsh vary greatly by species. For instance, the colorful calico rockﬁsh (Sebastes dalli) can survive for a little over a ______ the rougheye rockﬁsh (Sebastes aleutianus) boasts a maximum life span of about two centuries. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "decade: while","B": "decade. While","C": "decade; while","D": "decade, while","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a main clause and a subordinate clause. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the main clause (“the colorful…decade”) and the subordinate clause (“while…centuries”) that provides contrasting information about the life span of rougheye rockﬁsh. Choice A is incorrect because a colon can’t be used in this way to join a main clause and a subordinate clause. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with “while.” Choice C is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join a main clause and a subordinate clause.","Difficulty": "Medium"},
{"ID": "ce895702","Question": "In ancient Greece, an Epicurean was a follower of Epicurus, a philosopher whose beliefs revolved around the pursuit of pleasure. Epicurus deﬁned pleasure as “the absence of pain in the body and of trouble in the ______ that all life’s virtues derived from this absence. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "soul,” positing","B": "soul”: positing","C": "soul”; positing","D": "soul.” Positing","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between a main clause and a participial phrase. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the main clause (“Epicurus…‘soul’”) and the participial phrase (“positing…absence”) that provides additional information about how Epicurus deﬁned pleasure. Choice B is incorrect because a colon can’t be used in this way to join a main clause and a participial phrase. Choice C is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join a main clause and a participial phrase. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with “positing.”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "cefb265e","Question": "In 1903, environmentalist John Muir guided President Theodore Roosevelt on a scenic, sprawling trip through California’s Yosemite Valley. Upon returning from the three-day excursion, Roosevelt ______ to conserve the nation’s wilderness areas, a vow he upheld for his remaining six years in oﬃce. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "is vowing","B": "vowed","C": "will vow","D": "vows","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense in a sentence. In this choice, the past tense verb “vowed” is consistent with the other past tense verbs (“guided” and “upheld”) used to narrate the events surrounding President Roosevelt’s decision to conserve the nation’s wilderness areas. Choice A is incorrect because the present progressive tense verb “is vowing” isn’t consistent with the past tense verbs used to narrate the events surrounding President Roosevelt’s decision to conserve the nation’s wilderness areas. Choice C is incorrect because the future tense verb “will vow” isn’t consistent with the past tense verbs used to narrate the events surrounding President Roosevelt’s decision to conserve the nation’s wilderness areas. Choice D is incorrect because the simple present tense verb “vows” isn’t consistent with the past tense verbs used to narrate the events surrounding President Roosevelt’s decision to conserve the nation’s wilderness areas.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "d08ed203","Question": "If simple sugars such as ribose and glycolaldehyde ______ Earth from elsewhere and survived impact—a possibility astrophysicist Nicolle Zellner outlined in a 2020 study—the sugars could have reacted with other molecules that were already present on the planet to form the nucleotides that are the structural components of RNA and DNA. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "reach","B": "had reached","C": "will reach","D": "are reaching","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense. In this choice, the past perfect verb “had reached” is used correctly to describe a past action that was completed before another action in the past. Speciﬁcally, in this hypothetical scenario about the origins of RNA and DNA on Earth, the simple sugars had to have reached Earth before they could react with other molecules on the planet. Choice A is incorrect because the present tense verb “reach” doesn’t indicate that the simple sugars reached Earth before reacting with other molecules on the planet. Choice C is incorrect because the future tense verb “will reach” doesn’t indicate that the simple sugars reached Earth before reacting with other molecules on the planet. Choice D is incorrect because the present progressive verb “are reaching” doesn’t indicate that the simple sugars reached Earth before reacting with other molecules on the planet.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "d0d234ec","Question": "The Lion Light system, developed by Kenyan inventor Richard Turere, consists of LED lights installed around the perimeter of livestock pastures. Powered with ______ the blinking LEDs keep lions away at night, thus protecting the livestock without risking harm to the endangered lions. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "energy collected, by solar panels, during the day","B": "energy collected by solar panels during the day","C": "energy collected by solar panels during the day,","D": "energy, collected by solar panels during the day,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a supplementary phrase and a main clause. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the supplementary phrase (“powered…day”), which describes how the LEDs are powered, and the main clause (“the blinking…night”). Choice A is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the supplementary phrase and the main clause with appropriate punctuation. Furthermore, placing commas around the phrase “by solar panels” suggests that it could be removed without affecting the coherence of the sentence, which isn’t the case. Choice B is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the supplementary phrase and the main clause with appropriate punctuation. Choice D is incorrect. Placing commas around the phrase “collected by solar panels during the day″ suggests that it could be removed without affecting the coherence of the sentence, which isn’t the case.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "d19020f2","Question": "Known as Earth’s “living skin,” biocrusts are thin layers of soil held together by surface-dwelling microorganisms such as fungi, lichens, and cyanobacteria. Fortifying soil in arid ecosystems against erosion, ______ Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "a recent study’s estimate is that these crusts reduce global dust emissions by 60 percent each year.","B": "an estimated 60 percent reduction in global dust emissions each year is due to these crusts, according to a recent study.","C": "these crusts reduce global dust emissions by an estimated 60 percent each year, according to a recent study.","D": "a recent study has estimated that these crusts reduce global dust emissions by 60 percent each year.","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The subject of the modiﬁer 'fortifying soil in arid ecosystems against erosion' is 'biocrusts.' Subject-modiﬁer placement requires a modiﬁer and its subject to be next to each other, so 'biocrusts' or some variant meaning 'biocrusts' (in this case, 'these crusts') must begin the missing clause. Choice A is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The subject of the modiﬁer 'fortifying soil in arid ecosystems against erosion' is 'biocrusts,' not 'a recent study’s estimate.' Choice B is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The subject of the modiﬁer 'fortifying soil in arid ecosystems against erosion' is 'biocrusts,' not 'an estimated 60 percent reduction.' Choice D is incorrect. Modiﬁers and their subjects must go next to each other. The subject of the modiﬁer 'fortifying soil in arid ecosystems against erosion' is 'biocrusts,' not 'a recent study.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "d19cc07f","Question": "The Arctic-Alpine Botanic Garden in Norway and the Jardim Botânico of Rio de Janeiro in Brazil are two of many botanical gardens around the world dedicated to growing diverse plant ______ fostering scientiﬁc research; and educating the public about plant conservation. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "species, both native and nonnative,","B": "species, both native and nonnative;","C": "species; both native and nonnative,","D": "species both native and nonnative,","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of items in a complex series (a series including internal punctuation). The semicolon after “nonnative” is correctly used to separate the ﬁrst item (“growing diverse plant species, both native and nonnative”) and the second item (“fostering scientiﬁc research”) in the series of things that botanical gardens are dedicated to. Further, the comma after “species” is correctly used to separate the noun phrase “diverse plant species” and the supplementary phrase “both native and nonnative” that modiﬁes it. Choice A is incorrect because a comma (speciﬁcally, the comma after “nonnative”) can’t be used in this way to separate items in a complex series. Choice C is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to separate the noun phrase “diverse plant species” and the supplementary phrase “both native and nonnative” that modiﬁes it. Further, a comma can’t be used in this way to separate items in a complex series. Choice D is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the noun phrase “diverse plant species” and the supplementary phrase “both native and nonnative” that modiﬁes it. Further, a comma can’t be used in this way to separate items in a complex series.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "d52601c6","Question": "Earth is not a perfect sphere. Due to the ______ gravitational pull, Earth bulges out on the sides closest to and farthest from the Moon. This distorting pull is known as a tidal force, and it is responsible for the changes in water levels that are called high and low tides. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Moon’s","B": "Moons","C": "Moons’","D": "Moon","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of possessive nouns. The singular possessive noun 'Moon’s' correctly indicates that there is only one Moon, and it has a gravitational pull. Choice B is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive noun 'Moon’s,' not the plural noun 'Moons.' Choice C is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive noun 'Moon’s,' not the plural possessive noun 'Moons’.' Choice D is incorrect because the context requires the singular possessive noun 'Moon’s,' not the singular noun 'Moon.'","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "d63b0f5f","Question": "Robin Wall Kimmerer of the Citizen Potawatomi Nation is a bryologist, a plant scientist who specializes in mosses. To Kimmerer, mosses are Earth’s most adaptable plants: they can clone ______ enter a dormant state in times of drought, and grow in areas that don’t have soil. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "themselves;","B": "themselves,","C": "themselves. And","D": "themselves","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of items in a series. The comma after “themselves” is used conventionally to separate the ﬁrst item (“they can clone themselves”) and the second item (“enter a dormant state in times of drought”) in the series of things mosses can do. Choice A is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to separate items in a simple series such as this. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with “And enter.” Choice D is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the ﬁrst and second items in the series.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "d7ce1c0d","Question": "A recent study tracked the number of bee species present in twenty-seven New York apple orchards over a ten-year period. ______ found that when wild growth near an orchard was cleared, the number of different bee species visiting the orchard decreased. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Entomologist Heather Grab:","B": "Entomologist, Heather Grab,","C": "Entomologist Heather Grab","D": "Entomologist Heather Grab,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between a name and title and between a subject and a verb. No punctuation is needed between the proper noun “Heather Grab” and “entomologist,” the title that describes Grab. Additionally, no punctuation is needed between the sentence’s subject (“Entomologist Heather Grab”) and the main verb (“found”) that indicates what Grab did. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed. Setting the entomologist’s name off with commas suggests that it could be removed without affecting the coherence of the sentence, which isn’t the case. Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the subject and the verb.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "d8fef8ab","Question": "The classic children’s board game Chutes and Ladders is a version of an ancient Nepalese game, Paramapada Sopanapata. In both games, players encounter “good” or “bad” spaces while traveling along a path; landing on one of the good spaces ______ a player to skip ahead and arrive closer to the end goal. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "allows","B": "are allowing","C": "have allowed","D": "allow","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject–verb agreement. The singular verb “allows” agrees in number with the singular subject “landing.” Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb “are allowing” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “landing.” Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb “have allowed” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “landing.” Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb “allow” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “landing.”","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "dae097f3","Question": "With some 16,000 in attendance, the Second World Black and African Festival of Arts and ______ or FESTAC ‘77, as the event was more commonly known—became the largest pan-African event on record. FESTAC drew people from around the world to Lagos, Nigeria, for a monthlong celebration of Black and African art, scholarship, and activism. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Culture:","B": "Culture—","C": "lture,","D": "Culture","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The text uses a dash to introduce a nonessential element that explains the acronym FESTAC. The dash matches the dash that comes after “known,” ending the descriptive aside. Choice A is incorrect. A colon can only come after an independent clause, which isn’t the case here. Choice C is incorrect. While punctuation is required to set off “or FESTAC…known” from the rest of the sentence, nonessential elements must be separated from the sentence with matching punctuation. Since a dash appears on the other side of the element, we can’t use a comma here. Choice D is incorrect. The descriptive aside “or FESTAC…known” is a nonessential element that must be separated with punctuation from the rest of the sentence. This choice fails to add the necessary punctuation before the nonessential element.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "dd072786","Question": "Stomata, tiny pore structures in a leaf that absorb gases needed for plant growth, open when guard cells surrounding each pore swell with water. In a pivotal 2007 article, plant cell ______ showed that lipid molecules called phosphatidylinositol phosphates are responsible for signaling guard cells to open stomata. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "biologist, Yuree Lee","B": "biologist Yuree Lee,","C": "biologist Yuree Lee","D": "biologist, Yuree Lee,","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of punctuation between titles and proper nouns. No punctuation is needed to offset the proper noun “Yuree Lee” form the title “plant cell biologist” that describes Lee. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed. Choice D is incorrect because no punctuation is needed around the proper noun “Yuree Lee.” Setting the phrase off with punctuation suggests that it could be removed without affecting the coherence of the sentence, which isn’t the case.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "decfac99","Question": "Nigerian author Buchi Emecheta’s celebrated literary oeuvre includes The Joys of Motherhood, a novel about the changing roles of women in 1950s ______ a television play about the private struggles of a newlywed couple in Nigeria; and Head Above Water, her autobiography. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Lagos, Kind of Marriage,","B": "Lagos; A Kind of Marriage,","C": "Lagos, A Kind of Marriage:","D": "Lagos; A Kind of Marriage","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of items in a complex series (a series including internal punctuation). In this choice, the semicolon after “Lagos” is conventionally used to separate the ﬁrst item (“The Joys… Lagos”) and the second item (“A Kind…Nigeria”) in the series. Further, the comma after “Marriage” correctly separates the title “A Kind of Marriage” from the supplementary phrase (“a television…Nigeria”) that describes it. Choice A is incorrect because the comma after “Lagos” doesn’t match the semicolon used later in the series to separate the second item (“A Kind…Nigeria”) from the third item (“and…autobiography”). Choice C is incorrect because the comma after “Lagos” doesn’t match the semicolon used later in the series to separate the second item (“A Kind…Nigeria”) from the third item (“and…autobiography”). Additionally, a colon can’t be used in this way to separate the title “A Kind of Marriage” from the supplementary phrase (“a television…Nigeria”) that describes it. Choice D is incorrect because it fails to use appropriate punctuation to separate the title “A Kind of Marriage” from the supplementary phrase (“a television…Nigeria”) that describes it.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "dee177d4","Question": "Botanists recognize over ﬁfty different species of sunﬂower. One species, the silverleaf sunﬂower, ______ both an early- ﬂowering ecotype that tends to grow in coastal areas and a late-ﬂowering ecotype that grows inland. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "having included","B": "including","C": "to include","D": "includes","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. This verb needs to function as the main verb in the sentence, with the subject “one species,” so it needs to be conjugated. This choice gives us the singular present tense “includes,” which is the only conjugated form of the verb among the choices. Choice A is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. This verb needs to function as the main verb in the sentence, with the subject “one species,” so it needs to be conjugated. “Having included” is a participle form of the verb: it’s not conjugated and doesn’t function like a normal verb. Choice B is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. This verb needs to function as the main verb in the sentence, with the subject “one species,” so it needs to be conjugated. “Including” is the gerund form of the verb: it’s not conjugated and doesn’t function like a normal verb. Choice C is incorrect. This doesn’t complete the text in a way that conforms to the conventions of Standard English. This verb needs to function as the main verb in the sentence, with the subject “one species,” so it needs to be conjugated. “To include” is the inﬁnitive form of the verb: it’s not conjugated.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "df7c7932","Question": "In assessing the ﬁlms of Japanese director Akira Kurosawa, ______ have missed his equally deep engagement with Japanese artistic traditions such as Noh theater. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "many critics have focused on Kurosawa’s use of Western literary sources but","B": "Kurosawa’s use of Western literary sources has been the focus of many critics, who","C": "there are many critics who have focused on Kurosawa’s use of Western literary sources, but they","D": "the focus of many critics has been on Kurosawa’s use of Western literary sources; they","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice makes the noun phrase “many critics” the subject of the sentence and places it immediately after the modifying phrase “in assessing…Kurosawa.” In doing so, this choice clearly establishes that it is the critics—and not another noun in the sentence—who assess Kurosawa’s ﬁlms. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “Kurosawa’s…sources” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that his use of Western literary sources is what assesses Kurosawa’s ﬁlms. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the function word “there” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that “there” is what assesses Kurosawa’s ﬁlms. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “the focus…critics” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that the critics’ focus is what assesses Kurosawa’s ﬁlms.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "e3adf2fc","Question": "On sunny days, dark rooftops absorb solar energy and convert it to unwanted heat, raising the surrounding air ______ a light- colored covering to an existing dark roof, either by attaching prefabricated reﬂective sheets or spraying on a paint-like coating, helps combat this effect. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "temperature; by adding","B": "temperature, adding","C": "temperature. Adding","D": "temperature by adding","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between sentences. In this choice, the period is used correctly to mark the boundary between the ﬁrst sentence (“On…temperature”) and the second sentence (“Adding… effect”). The gerund phrase beginning with “adding” is the subject of the second sentence, and the verb phrase “helps combat this effect” describes what adding a light-colored covering can do. Choice A is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join the sentence “On...temperature” and the supplementary phrases that follow. Doing so leaves the verb phrase “helps combat” without a subject and thus results in a grammatically unconventional sentence. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a comma splice. A comma can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between sentences. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a confusing and illogical sentence that suggests that adding a light-colored covering to an existing dark roof raises the temperature of the surrounding air. Furthermore, it creates ambiguity by leaving the verb phrase “helps combat” without a subject (so it isn’t clear what helps combat the effect).","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "e45302f3","Question": "Award-winning cinematographer James Wong Howe was known for his innovative ﬁlming techniques. While ﬁlming a boxing match for the movie Body and Soul ______ Howe had a handheld camera operator wear roller skates. This allowed the operator to move smoothly around actors in a boxing ring, creating an immersive experience for viewers. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "(1947), and","B": "(1947),","C": "(1947) and","D": "(1947)","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a supplementary element and a main clause. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the supplementary phrase (“While...1947”), which indicates when the action occurred, and the main clause (“Howe had a handheld camera operator wear roller skates”). Choice A is incorrect because a comma paired with the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between the supplementary element (“While…1947”) and the main clause (“Howe…skates”). Choice C is incorrect because the conjunction “and” can’t be used in this way to join the supplementary element (“While…1947”) and the main clause (“Howe…skates”). Choice D is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the supplementary element and the main clause with appropriate punctuation.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "e5d07e9f","Question": "In many of her landscape paintings from the 1970s and 1980s, Lebanese American artist Etel Adnan worked to capture the essence of California’s fog-shrouded Mount Tamalpais region through abstraction, using splotches of color to represent the area’s features. Interestingly, the triangle representing the mountain itself ______ among the few deﬁned ﬁgures in her paintings. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "are","B": "have been","C": "were","D": "is","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject–verb agreement. The singular verb “is” agrees in number with the singular subject “the triangle.” Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb “are” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “the triangle.” Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb “have been” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “the triangle.” Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb “were” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “the triangle.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "e6d9dc6f","Question": "In 1899, Swedish chemist Svante Arrhenius developed an equation to answer a long-standing question: why do chemical reactions speed up at higher temperatures? The Arrhenius equation, named for its creator, ______ an important concept in modern chemistry. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "have remained","B": "remain","C": "remains","D": "are remaining","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. This choice uses the singular verb 'remains' to match the singular subject 'equation.' Choice A is incorrect. The singular noun 'equation' doesn’t match with the plural verb conjugation 'have remained.' Choice B is incorrect. The singular noun 'equation' doesn’t match with the plural verb conjugation 'remain.' Choice D is incorrect. The singular noun 'equation' doesn’t match with the plural verb conjugation 'are remaining.'","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "e76c35d5","Question": "Author Madeline L’Engle, ______ to create a suspenseful tone that draws the reader in, begins her novel A Wrinkle in Time with descriptions of “wraithlike shadows” and “the frenzied lashing of the wind.” Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "looked","B": "looks","C": "is looking","D": "looking","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verb forms within a sentence. The nonﬁnite present participle verb “looking” is correctly used to form a subordinate clause that describes the intent behind how L’Engle begins her novel. Choice A is incorrect because the ﬁnite past tense verb “looked” can’t be used in this way to form a subordinate clause. Choice B is incorrect because the ﬁnite present tense verb “looks” can’t be used in this way to form a subordinate clause. Choice C is incorrect because the ﬁnite present progressive tense verb “is looking” can’t be used in this way to form a subordinate clause.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "e9739feb","Question": "Why are Rome’s famous concrete structures, such as the Colosseum, still standing after 2,000-plus years, when modern concrete may not even last for ﬁfty? Scientists ______ that the secret to Roman concrete’s durability was its unique blend of ingredients, which included volcanic ash and seawater. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "explain","B": "having explained","C": "explaining","D": "to explain","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verb forms within a sentence. The main clause of a sentence requires a ﬁnite (tensed) verb, and this choice supplies the ﬁnite present tense verb “explain” to indicate what the scientists do. Choice B is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The nonﬁnite participle “having explained” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice C is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The nonﬁnite participle “explaining” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice D is incorrect because it results in an ungrammatical sentence. The nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to explain” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "ea7df903","Question": "In 1959, marine biologist Dr. Albert Jones founded the Underwater Adventure Seekers, a scuba diving ______ that is the oldest club for Black divers in the United States and that has helped thousands of diving enthusiasts become certiﬁed in the ﬁeld. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "club","B": "club,","C": "club—","D": "club, and","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. “That is…ﬁeld” is an essential supplement, so we should not use punctuation to separate it from “scuba diving club.” . Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. “That is…ﬁeld” is an essential supplement, so we should not use a comma (or any kind of punctuation) to separate it from “scuba diving club.” . Choice C is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. “That is…ﬁeld” is an essential supplement, so we should not use a dash (or any kind of punctuation) to separate it from “scuba diving club.” . Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a run-on sentence. It makes “that is…United States” into an awkward independent clause, but it also makes “that has…ﬁeld” into its own awkward independent clause without the correct punctuation separating it.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "eb098d8a","Question": "Polyphenols are organic compounds ______ among their many roles, provide pigment that helps protect plants against ultraviolet radiation from sunlight. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "that—","B": "that;","C": "that,","D": "that:","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is the punctuation of a supplementary element within a sentence. The comma after “that” pairs with the comma after “roles” to separate the supplementary element “among their many roles” from the rest of the sentence. This supplementary element functions to clarify that polyphenols have many roles, and the pair of commas indicates that this element could be removed without affecting the grammatical coherence of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because a dash can’t be paired with a comma to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice B is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be paired with a comma to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence. Choice D is incorrect because a colon can’t be paired with a comma to separate the supplementary element from the rest of the sentence.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "eb64c05f","Question": "When external forces are applied to common glass made from silicates, energy builds up around minuscule defects in the material, resulting in fractures. Recently, engineer Erkka Frankberg of Tampere University in Finland used the chemical ______ to make a glassy solid that can withstand higher strain than silicate glass can before fracturing. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "compound, aluminum oxide","B": "compound aluminum oxide,","C": "compound, aluminum oxide,","D": "compound aluminum oxide","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of punctuation around noun phrases. No punctuation is needed because the noun phrase “aluminum oxide” is a restrictive appositive, meaning that it provides essential identifying information about the noun phrase before it, “the chemical compound,” and thus doesn’t require punctuation around it. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed. Choice C is incorrect because the noun phrase “aluminum oxide” is a restrictive appositive. Setting the phrase off with punctuation suggests that it could be removed without affecting the coherence of the sentence, which isn’t the case.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "eca749e2","Question": "In the novel Things Fall Apart by Chinua Achebe, Okonkwo is a leader of Umuoﬁa (a ﬁctional Nigerian clan) and takes pride in his culture’s traditions. However, when the arrival of European missionaries brings changes to Umuoﬁa, the novel asks a central question: How ______ Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Umuoﬁa’s traditions will be affected.","B": "will Umuoﬁa’s traditions be affected.","C": "Umuoﬁa’s traditions will be affected?","D": "will Umuoﬁa’s traditions be affected?","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The clause before the colon tells us that the novel “asks a question,” so the clause after the colon should be in the conventional form of a question: with the verb before the subject, and a question mark at the end. Choice A is incorrect. This choice ends the sentence with a period, which isn’t right. The clause before the colon tells us that the novel “asks a question,” so the clause after the colon should be that question. Choice B is incorrect. This choice ends the sentence with a period, which isn’t right. The clause before the colon tells us that the novel “asks a question,” so the clause after the colon should be that question. In Standard English, questions place the verb before the subject and end with a question mark. Choice C is incorrect. This choice doesn’t conform to the conventions of Standard English. In Standard English, questions place the verb before the subject.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "ecbf2a17","Question": "Compared to that of alumina glass, ______ silica glass atoms are so far apart that they are unable to re-form bonds after being separated. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "silica glass is at a signiﬁcant disadvantage due to its more dispersed atomic arrangement:","B": "silica glass has a more dispersed atomic arrangement, resulting in a signiﬁcant disadvantage:","C": "a signiﬁcant disadvantage of silica glass is that its atomic arrangement is more dispersed:","D": "silica glass’s atomic arrangement is more dispersed, resulting in a signiﬁcant disadvantage:","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice makes “silica glass’s atomic arrangement” the subject of the sentence and places it immediately after the modifying phrase “compared to that of alumina glass.” In doing so, this choice clearly establishes that silica glass’s atomic arrangement—and not another noun in the sentence—is being compared to the atomic arrangement (“that”) of alumina glass. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “silica glass” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that silica glass itself (rather than its atomic arrangement) is being compared to alumina glass’s atomic arrangement. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “silica glass” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that silica glass itself (rather than its atomic arrangement) is being compared to alumina glass’s atomic arrangement. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “a signiﬁcant disadvantage” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that “a signiﬁcant disadvantage” is being compared to alumina glass’s atomic arrangement.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "eccc78e0","Question": "In 1453, English King Henry VI became unﬁt to rule after falling gravely ill. As a result, Parliament appointed Richard, Third Duke of York, who had a strong claim to the English throne, to rule as Lord Protector. Upon recovering two years later, ______ forcing an angered Richard from the royal court and precipitating a series of battles later known as the Wars of the Roses. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Henry resumed his reign,","B": "the reign of Henry resumed,","C": "Henry’s reign resumed,","D": "it was Henry who resumed his reign,","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice ensures that the introductory phrase “upon recovering two years later” appears immediately before the noun it modiﬁes (“Henry”), clearly establishing that Henry recovered two years later. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “the reign of Henry” immediately after the introductory phrase illogically suggests that the reign of Henry recovered two years later. Choice C is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “Henry’s reign” immediately after the introductory phrase illogically suggests that Henry’s reign recovered two years later. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the function word “it” immediately after the introductory phrase illogically suggests that “it” recovered two years later.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "ee2e4c20","Question": "Nuhād al-addād, known as Fairuz, was one of the most beloved Lebanese singers of the twentieth century. Her broad singing repertoire—which included traditional forms, such as the Arabic qasida and maqam, alongside modern pop and jazz styles—lent Fairuz a timeless, cross-generational appeal, ______ her the moniker “the soul of Lebanon.” Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "earned","B": "had earned","C": "earning","D": "earn","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The word 'earning' is being used to introduce an additional modifying phrase, which describes how Fairuz’s repertoire lent her cross-generational appeal. When a verb ends in -ing and doesn’t have a helper verb like 'is' before it, it can be used to modify a noun or verb. This is appropriate here. Choice A is incorrect. The underlined verb is being used to introduce additional descriptive information, which is set off from the rest of the sentence by a comma. Because there is no subject here, a ﬁnite form of the verb (like 'earned') creates an error. We need another form of the verb that doesn’t require a subject and can introduce descriptive information. Choice B is incorrect. The underlined verb is being used to introduce additional descriptive information, which is set off from the rest of the sentence by a comma. Because there is no subject here, a ﬁnite form of the verb (like 'had earned') creates an error. We need another form of the verb that doesn’t require a subject and can introduce descriptive information. Choice D is incorrect. The underlined verb is being used to introduce additional descriptive information, which is set off from the rest of the sentence by a comma. Because there is no subject here, a ﬁnite form of the verb (like 'earn') creates an error. We need another form of the verb that doesn’t require a subject and can introduce descriptive information.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "f0b5eb43","Question": "The 1977 play And the Soul Shall Dance depicts two Japanese American farming families in Depression-era Southern California. Critics have noted the way pioneering ______ compares the experiences of issei (Japanese nationals who emigrated to America) and nisei (their American-born children). Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "playwright, Wakako Yamauchi,","B": "playwright, Wakako Yamauchi","C": "playwright Wakako Yamauchi,","D": "playwright Wakako Yamauchi","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of punctuation between titles and proper nouns. No punctuation is needed to set off the proper noun 'Wakako Yamauchi' from the title that describes Yamauchi, 'pioneering playwright.' Because 'Wakako Yamauchi' is essential information identifying the 'pioneering playwright,' no punctuation is necessary. Choice A is incorrect because no punctuation is needed before or after the proper noun 'Wakako Yamauchi.' Setting the playwright’s name off with commas suggests that it could be removed without affecting the coherence of the sentence, which isn’t the case. Choice B is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the title 'pioneering playwright' and the proper noun 'Wakako Yamauchi.' Choice C is incorrect because no punctuation is needed between the proper noun 'Wakako Yamauchi' and the verb 'compares.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "f102f1be","Question": "Atoms in a synchrotron, a type of circular particle accelerator, travel faster and faster until they ______ a desired energy level, at which point they are diverted to collide with a target, smashing the atoms. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "will reach","B": "reach","C": "had reached","D": "are reaching","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense in a sentence. In this choice, the present tense verb “reach” is consistent with the present tense verbs “travel” and “are diverted” used to describe how atoms move through the synchrotron. Choice A is incorrect because the future tense verb “will reach” is inconsistent with the present tense verbs used to describe how atoms move through the synchrotron. Though the atoms’ movement is a recurring action and “will reach” can also be used to indicate a habitual or recurring action, it creates a logical inconsistency in this sentence when paired with the present tense verbs “travel” and “are diverted.” Choice C is incorrect because the past perfect tense verb “had reached” is inconsistent with the present tense verbs used to describe how atoms move through the synchrotron. Choice D is incorrect because the present progressive tense verb “are reaching” is inconsistent with the present tense verbs used to describe how atoms move through the synchrotron. While both verbs occur in the present, the present progressive tense suggests that the action is currently in progress. This creates a logical inconsistency when paired with the present tense verbs “travel” and “are diverted,” which offer a general description of the tendencies of the atoms’ movement, rather than a description of an action that is currently in progress.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "f102f1be","Question": "Atoms in a synchrotron, a type of circular particle accelerator, travel faster and faster until they ______ a desired energy level, at which point they are diverted to collide with a target, smashing the atoms. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "will reach","B": "reach","C": "had reached","D": "are reaching","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of verbs to express tense in a sentence. In this choice, the present tense verb “reach” is consistent with the present tense verbs “travel” and “are diverted” used to describe how atoms move through the synchrotron. Choice A is incorrect because the future tense verb “will reach” is inconsistent with the present tense verbs used to describe how atoms move through the synchrotron. Though the atoms’ movement is a recurring action and “will reach” can also be used to indicate a habitual or recurring action, it creates a logical inconsistency in this sentence when paired with the present tense verbs “travel” and “are diverted.” Choice C is incorrect because the past perfect tense verb “had reached” is inconsistent with the present tense verbs used to describe how atoms move through the synchrotron. Choice D is incorrect because the present progressive tense verb “are reaching” is inconsistent with the present tense verbs used to describe how atoms move through the synchrotron. While both verbs occur in the present, the present progressive tense suggests that the action is currently in progress. This creates a logical inconsistency when paired with the present tense verbs “travel” and “are diverted,” which offer a general description of the tendencies of the atoms’ movement, rather than a description of an action that is currently in progress.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "f21677cb","Question": "How do scientists determine what foods were eaten by extinct hominins such as Neanderthals? In the past, researchers were limited to studying the marks found on the fossilized teeth of skeletons, but in 2017 a team led by Laura Weyrich of the Australian Centre for Ancient DNA tried something ______ the DNA found in Neanderthals’ fossilized dental plaque. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "new: sequencing","B": "new; sequencing","C": "new, sequencing:","D": "new. Sequencing","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. “A team…tried something new” is an independent clause leading to an explanation of what the new thing was. A colon can only be used at the end of an independent clause, and typically introduces further explanation that expands upon the ﬁrst clause, which makes a colon the perfect choice here. Choice B is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error. “Sequencing…dental plaque” can’t stand on its own as a sentence, and so it can’t be linked to the independent clause “a team…tried something new” with a semicolon. Only two independent clauses can be connected in this way. Choice C is incorrect. This choice results in a punctuation error. If “sequencing” is included in the ﬁrst clause, it can no longer stand on its own as a complete idea. Since a colon can only come at the end of an independent clause, using one in this way creates an error. Choice D is incorrect. This choice results in a sentence fragment. “Sequencing…dental plaque” can’t stand on its own as a sentence.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "f2ff982f","Question": "Researchers studying the “terra-cotta army,” the thousands of life-size statues of warriors found interred near the tomb of Emperor Qin Shi Huang of China, were shocked to realize that the shape of each statue’s ears, like the shape of each person’s ears, ______ unique. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "are","B": "is","C": "were","D": "have been","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject–verb agreement. because the singular verb “is” agrees in number with the singular subject “the shape.” Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb “are” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “the shape.” Choice C is incorrect because the plural verb “were” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “the shape.” Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb “have been” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “the shape.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "f3bd8ebc","Question": "A study published by Rice University geoscientist Ming Tang in 2019 offers a new explanation for the origin of Earth’s ______ structures called arcs, towering ridges that form when a dense oceanic plate subducts under a less dense continental plate, melts in the mantle below, and then rises and bursts through the continental crust above. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "continents geological","B": "continents: geological","C": "continents; geological","D": "continents. Geological","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation use between a main clause and a supplementary phrase. In this choice, a colon is correctly used to mark the boundary between the main clause (“A study…continents”) and the supplementary phrase (“geological…above”) and to introduce the following explanation of the origin of Earth’s continents. Choice A is incorrect because it fails to mark the boundary between the main clause (“A study…continents”) and the supplementary phrase (“geological…above”) with appropriate punctuation. Choice C is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to join the main clause (“A study…continents”) and the supplementary phrase (“geological…above”). A semicolon is conventionally used to join two main clauses, whereas a colon is conventionally used to introduce an element that explains or ampliﬁes the information in the preceding clause, making it the better choice in this context. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a rhetorically unacceptable sentence fragment beginning with “geological.”","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "f460370e","Question": "Before the Erie Canal was completed in 1825, transporting goods by wagon between New York City and the Midwest took up to forty-ﬁve days and cost one hundred dollars per ton. By linking the Hudson River to Lake ______ canal reduced transport time to nine days and cut costs to six dollars per ton. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Erie; the","B": "Erie (the","C": "Erie, the","D": "Erie: the","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is punctuation between a supplementary phrase and a main clause. This choice correctly uses a comma to mark the boundary between the introductory supplementary phrase (“By linking the Hudson River to Lake Erie”), which identiﬁes how the canal reduced transport time, and the main clause (“the canal reduced transport time to nine days and cut costs to six dollars per ton”). Choice A is incorrect because a semicolon can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between a supplementary phrase (“By…Erie”) and the main clause (“the canal...ton”). Choice B is incorrect because an open parenthesis can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between a supplementary phrase (“By…Erie”) and the main clause (“the canal...ton”). Choice D is incorrect because a colon can’t be used in this way to mark the boundary between an introductory supplementary phrase (“By…Erie”) and the main clause (“the canal...ton”).","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "f4d86ecd","Question": "When writing The Other Black Girl (2021), novelist Zakiya Dalila Harris drew on her own experiences working at a publishing oﬃce. The award-winning book is Harris’s ﬁrst novel, but her writing ______ honored before. At the age of twelve, she entered a contest to have a story published in American Girl magazine—and won. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "were","B": "have been","C": "has been","D": "are","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-verb agreement. The singular verb “has been” agrees in number with the singular subject “writing.” Choice A is incorrect because the plural verb “were” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “writing.” Choice B is incorrect because the plural verb “have been” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “writing.” Choice D is incorrect because the plural verb “are” doesn’t agree in number with the singular subject “writing.”","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "f5794d32","Question": "Quantum particles of light—photons—provide an unhackable means of transmitting encryption keys over networks, as attempts to observe particles in quantum states will invariably alter the particles ______ dismantle any information they transmit. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "and in the process,","B": "and, in the process,","C": "and in the process—","D": "and, in the process","Answer": "B","Rationale": "Choice B is the best answer. This choice uses paired punctuation in the form of two commas to set off the nonessential phrase 'in the process.' Choice A is incorrect. The phrase 'in the process' is a nonessential element and needs to be set off with paired punctuation. We need a comma after 'and' to match the one after 'process.' Choice C is incorrect. The phrase 'in the process' is a nonessential element and needs to be set off with paired punctuation, so we would need a dash after 'and' to match the one following 'process.' Choice D is incorrect. The phrase 'in the process' is a nonessential element and needs to be set off with paired punctuation. We would need a comma after 'process' to match the one following 'and.'","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "f78e1f28","Question": "Lucía Michel of the University of Chile observed that alkaline soils contain an insoluble form of iron that blueberry plants cannot absorb, thus inhibiting blueberry growth. If these plants were grown in alkaline soil alongside grasses that aid in iron solubilization, ______ Michel was determined to ﬁnd out. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "could the blueberries thrive.","B": "the blueberries could thrive.","C": "the blueberries could thrive?","D": "could the blueberries thrive?","Answer": "D","Rationale": "Choice D is the best answer. The convention being tested is end-of-sentence punctuation. This choice correctly uses a question mark to punctuate the interrogative clause “could the blueberries thrive,” which asks a direct question at the end of the sentence. Choice A is incorrect because a period can’t be used in this way to punctuate an interrogative clause, such as “could the blueberries thrive,” at the end of a sentence. Choice B is incorrect because the context requires an interrogative clause. The declarative clause “the blueberries could thrive” incorrectly indicates that it was known that the blueberries could thrive in alkaline soil, whereas Michel had yet to ﬁnd this out. Choice C is incorrect because a question mark can’t be used in this way to punctuate a declarative clause, such as “the blueberries could thrive,” at the end of a sentence.","Difficulty": "Medium"},{"ID": "fa99e172","Question": "While one requires oxygen and one does ______ and anaerobic respiration are both forms of cellular respiration—that is, they are processes by which cells break down glucose to use as energy. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "not aerobic","B": "not. Aerobic","C": "not, aerobic","D": "not; aerobic","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. A comma is the appropriate way to link the dependent clause “While...not” and the independent clause that follows. Choice A is incorrect. This choice creates a run-on sentence error. “While...not” is a dependent clause, which must be separated from the independent clause that follows with some sort of punctuation. Choice B is incorrect. This choice creates a sentence fragment. “While one requires oxygen and one does not” isn’t an independent clause, so it can’t stand alone as a complete sentence. Choice D is incorrect. This choice creates a punctuation error. “While one requires oxygen and one does not” isn’t an independent clause, so it can’t be linked to the clause that follows with a semicolon.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "fc7ebf09","Question": "Even though bats prefer very sweet nectar, the plants that attract them have evolved to produce nectar that is only moderately sweet. A recent study ______ why: making sugar is energy-intensive, and it is more advantageous for plants to make a large amount of low-sugar nectar than a small amount of high-sugar nectar. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "explains","B": "explaining","C": "having explained","D": "to explain","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. The convention being tested is the use of ﬁnite and nonﬁnite verb forms within a sentence. A main clause requires a ﬁnite verb to perform the action of the subject (in this case, “a recent study”), and this choice supplies the ﬁnite present tense verb “explains” to indicate that the study explains why plants that attract bats have evolved to produce moderately sweet nectar. Choice B is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “explaining” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice C is incorrect because the nonﬁnite participle “having explained” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb. Choice D is incorrect because the nonﬁnite to-inﬁnitive “to explain” doesn’t supply the main clause with a ﬁnite verb.","Difficulty": "Easy"},{"ID": "fc9633e4","Question": "African American Percy Julian was a scientist and entrepreneur whose work helped people around the world to see. Named in 1999 as one of the greatest achievements by a US chemist in the past hundred years, ______ led to the ﬁrst mass-produced treatment for glaucoma. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "Julian synthesized the alkaloid physostigmine in 1935; it","B": "in 1935 Julian synthesized the alkaloid physostigmine, which","C": "Julian’s 1935 synthesis of the alkaloid physostigmine","D": "the alkaloid physostigmine was synthesized by Julian in 1935 and","Answer": "C","Rationale": "Choice C is the best answer. The convention being tested is subject-modiﬁer placement. This choice makes the noun phrase “Julian’s 1935 synthesis” the subject of the sentence and places it immediately after the modifying phrase “named…years.” In doing so, this choice clearly establishes that Julian’s 1935 synthesis of the alkaloid physostigmine—and not another noun in the sentence—was named in 1999 as one of the greatest achievements by a US chemist in the past hundred years. Choice A is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun “Julian” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically suggests that Julian himself was named as one of the greatest achievements by a US chemist in the past hundred years. Choice B is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the prepositional phrase “in 1935” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically and confusingly suggests that “in 1935” was named as one of the greatest achievements by a US chemist in the past hundred years. Choice D is incorrect because it results in a dangling modiﬁer. The placement of the noun phrase “the alkaloid physostigmine” immediately after the modifying phrase illogically and confusingly suggests that the alkaloid physostigmine itself (not the synthesis of it) was named as one of the greatest achievements by a US chemist in the past hundred years.","Difficulty": "Hard"},{"ID": "fe9fff45","Question": "By the time Hawaiian king Kamehameha III ______ the throne, the number of longhorn cattle, ﬁrst introduced to the islands in 1793, had drastically increased, and so too had the need for paniolo (Hawaiian cowboys) to manage the wild herds that then roamed throughout the volcanic terrain. Which choice completes the text so that it conforms to the conventions of Standard English?","A": "ascended","B": "will ascend","C": "ascends","D": "is ascending","Answer": "A","Rationale": "Choice A is the best answer. 'Ascended' is in the simple past tense. Since Kamehameha became king in the past, this makes the most sense. Choice B is incorrect. 'Will ascend' is in the future tense, but we wouldn’t know about Kamehameha III’s ascent if it hadn’t happened yet. The information in the sentence, as well as the tense of other verbs, tells us that the events described happened in the past. Choice C is incorrect. 'Ascends' is in the simple present tense. However, the information in the sentence, as well as the tense of other verbs, tells us that the events described happened in the past. Choice D is incorrect. 'Is ascending' is in the continuous present tense, which we use to show that something is ongoing, but this doesn’t make sense here—the information in the sentence, as well as the tense of other verbs, tells us that the events described happened in the past.","Difficulty": "Medium"}]